<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://blog.knews.space/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://blog.knews.space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-15T00:45:36+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/</id><title type="html">kNews.space | Launch Briefings and Vlogs</title><subtitle>Rocket Launch Briefings and Space Vlogs</subtitle><author><name>Lukas</name></author><entry><title type="html">A “ Brief “ Introduction</title><link href="http://blog.knews.space/briefings/a-brief-introduction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A &quot; Brief &quot; Introduction" /><published>2018-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/briefings/a-brief-introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.knews.space/briefings/a-brief-introduction.html">&lt;p&gt;Rocket Launch Briefings will initially give you a quick or &lt;em&gt;brief&lt;/em&gt; overview about a month’s rocket launches. I have not yet decided whether I will cover them monthly or weekly but monthly is definitely a more eye catchy format I think. “Rocket Launch Briefing - November 2018” sounds more like something people would watch in retrospect. Meaning, it’s not that much effort to watch 12 episodes in order to get an overview about a full year, rather than 52 episodes! I will of course pick out topics I find most interesting and make separate videos about them in the other new video format I currently call my “Video Logbook” aka. a Vlog. I will talk rather casually about something while playing back an animation that I got inspired to. Nothing too fancy and also rather compact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefings will have a reoccuring scene where the camera moves through a futuristic hallway. I’ll try to get more SciFi vibes going on in the future! As the camera moves forward it will swivel left and right to check out each individual rocket, its payload and stats. While it does so I will in good old kNews tradition enhance the experience with original animations, real imagery or other fitting things. I’m already a big fan of this format and can’t wait to share it with you! The first one will be as already mentioned about November 2018 and I am currently finishing it up so stay tuned for that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this will evolve over time but if you know my videos than you know that if I do one thing, then it is to never be satisfied with how something looks. I have never released two videos without any kind of progress going on. These are often small nuances but sometimes also radical changes as the new Briefings and Vlogs will be! The main reason and driver behind this is not the progress itself though. I had some serious issues as my videos have gotten so complex that it simply took ages to finish them. Each was such a big project that it took almost a month or part time work to get it done. That’s just too much! I hope introducing these changes will not only make it better from a viewers perspective but also better when it comes to production and rendering effort. We’ll see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="new content" /><category term="briefings" /><category term="knews" /><summary type="html">Rocket Launch Briefings will initially give you a quick or brief overview about a month’s rocket launches. I have not yet decided whether I will cover them monthly or weekly but monthly is definitely a more eye catchy format I think. “Rocket Launch Briefing - November 2018” sounds more like something people would watch in retrospect. Meaning, it’s not that much effort to watch 12 episodes in order to get an overview about a full year, rather than 52 episodes! I will of course pick out topics I find most interesting and make separate videos about them in the other new video format I currently call my “Video Logbook” aka. a Vlog. I will talk rather casually about something while playing back an animation that I got inspired to. Nothing too fancy and also rather compact!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%222018/brief_000_explanation.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is SpaceX Starlink?</title><link href="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-starlink-explained.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is SpaceX Starlink?" /><published>2018-11-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-starlink-explained</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-starlink-explained.html">&lt;p&gt;The dotted white outer rim to the sides shows regular communication satellites in a geosynchronous orbit. There are roughly 500 or these currently in orbit and most of you will know them from satellite television. Yep, that’s where you point your dishes at. The ISS orbits much more closely at 400 km, in fact it’s so close you wouldn’t even notice its in space at all from up here. The red dot zips across the sky at 8 km/s in order to not fall back to ground. It counters gravity with its own inertia like a giant centrifuge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_004/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial SpaceX Starlink Constellation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Starlink constellation will have a very similar orbit but there will be many many more. This is no coincidence because SpaceX will launch from the same launch site in Florida and that’s the highest inclination they can still reach somewhat efficiently. The first batch you can see here consists of almost 1600 satellites distributed over 24 orbital planes with 66 satellites each not counting on orbit spares. These spare satellites are basically a buffer to make sure a failing satellite can be replaced quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first constellation will operate from an altitude of 550 km and will be able to communicate with itself and the ground using microwaves similar to your smartphones. But don’t get too excited about that. (www.kNews.space) 550 km is not in reach of any regular smartphone so you will not be able to browse the web like that, at least not in regular fashion but we’ll discuss that later. The plan is to use dishes on terminals which can track the satellites by simply following them. This will change and modernize over time as SpaceX usually does. They will iterate on the design of these satellites and terminals starting with the most basic of hardware evolving them into whatever proves the best over time. They have actually launched two test articles to space already as a secondary payload. Tintin A and B named after the belgian comic’s character Tintin or “TinTin” (french pronunciation). They work for in the order of 15 minutes day as they fly by the US with high bandwidth and 25 ms of latency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of latency, this used to be the issue with satellite communication as it was for the the most part using those geosynchronous orbits far out. The speed of light is 300.000 km/s so in order for a signal to bounce back and forth twice for a ping-pong or ping test, it would travel at least 140.000 km or roughly half a second. That’s a big delay which is fine for one directional streaming but incredibly painful for anything else, especially online gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait a second, one directional streaming? Yep, I would argue what many don’t count with when it comes to Skylink is streaming. You could in theory use regular cellular internet to ask for data and then use Starnet to provide it in even the most remote of areas directly onto a mobile device. However, that’s just my speculation and it really depends on whether the signal strength is strong enough to be picked up with an  antenna that fits inside a smartphone. (www.kNews.space) But I can imagine companies could sell pocket dishes with receivers only which don’t require special radio licenses. Anyhow, important to note is SpaceX could bring satellite television to smartphones no matter where you are. I used to think Starlink was completely supplementary to the existing market as ground based 5G systems will offer higher speeds and a quicker latency, but as it turns out they could really threaten those valuable satellite television companies that ironically fund SpaceX today by launching satellites with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that of course depends on whether SpaceX will make use of it or not. In the end there is enough streaming you can do online which will probably exploit most of the bandwidth already. What SpaceX could also do is to mount GPS transmitters to offer positioning services. Thinking about it again that could turn into a problem though since no government had direct control over it so bad actors could abuse it to guide missiles. Regular GPS can be turned on and off or even manipulated to send missles back to where they were coming from. The whole globe is tracked via infrared sensors from space so any device that exhausts a lot of heat is immediately picked up by the military which is vital not only to defend attacks but also to prevent people from even attempting it. I guess SpaceX won’t offer positioning services at least without governmental control over it or only with very low precision to tell in which country you are but not on which grassholm your sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_004/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full SpaceX Starlink Constellation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what remains is the internet which is of course the most important communication infrastructure nowadays. It will as mentioned offer high bandwidth in the gigabit range per user but with a comparatively okay latency of round about 10 ms to local servers or and this is the main advantage 30 to 60 ms all across the globe. Yep, it will even beat a direct optical fiber connection because signals in these fibers travel at only 60-70% of the speed of light. The longer the distance the higher the advantage of such a space based system. 30 - 60 ms is not great for online shooters but totally fine for most other games and of course calls. But I didn’t came up with that one by myself. There is a great video by I think a professor called Mark Handley. He wrote a software to simulate the constellation’s links and latency of the system pretty much proving the point. I highly recommend to watch it! I have never really thought about satellites being faster than a direct optical fiber link across the ocean. And this initial constellation will as mentioned only be the first and there are many more to come. The final low earth constellation will consist of almost 5000 satellites on different orbits and this is still not all. This will more than double in the long run as SpaceX will try to utilize a very low earth orbits below 350 km and therefore below the ISS. This one is further out and will probably not fund BFR like the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, this whole constellation is supposed to fund SpaceX next gen rocket so it is not a 20 year plan, but supposed to be finished in just a few years from now. How can they do it you may ask? This more than doubles all satellites that are in space today. And won’t it cause crashes and debris? Yep, it is not an easy task but each teal sphere you can see here has actually a purpose. It is 60 km wide and that is exactly the safe zone around a satellite SpaceX will keep free. Given a perfectly optimized constellation, which mine isn’t, none of these spheres should ever intersect with another. That is a lot of safe zone even if one satellite should fail. It would take many months to drift 60 km off course in which SpaceX could in theory rendezvous with some kind of on orbit garbage collector that could deorbit uncontrolled satellites. What sets SpaceX apart from others is they are at the source or they are the source for that matter. Unlike other companies that try to do the same they can use free rockets. Yes, their used boosters are already paid for so they can start out by simply using and reusing those without having to buy new ones. This is an incredible advantage over any competitor which won’t be able to operate a similar fleet at a competitive price point. Maybe amazon with their New Glenn rocket but that’s another video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now of course, satellites won’t only fail by accident. If you do the math 5000 satellites with a lifespan of 5 years each means 20 satellites failing per week on average. They will not only have to deorbit them on their own but will also need an insane launch rate to maintain the whole fleet and they can’t yet reuse their upper stage. Building so many upper stages and satellite will make funding BFR a real challenge. (ww w. kN ews. spac e) So, and this is just my conclusion, they have to reuse their upper stage for Skynet, I mean Starlink. They can’t wait for BFR because this is meant to fund it and they can hardly fund it by building so many satellites and upper stages. Of course Elon Musk himself tweeted it out recently. They will try to turn the upper stage in some sort of Mini-BFR as I have already talked about in a previous video. Feel free to check that one out if you haven’t or want to refresh your memory. Now let’s assume they really do it and manage to reuse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s with all the debris falling to ground? 20 satellites burning up a weak or a 1000 per year is insane. According to their simulations there is a high chance of a couple kgs of metal surviving reentry and these pieces will re-enter and crash into the ground somewhere. Of course, most will do so into the ocean but some will inevitably crash into ground. They could harm people and cause fires. That’s quite a long term risk to take so I personally believe SpaceX will at least in the long run, as their technology evolves, have to come up with something new - again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_004/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hypothetical Reusable Satellite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reusable satellites! Yep, mounting a small heatshield, maybe protective housing and parachute is all it takes. Mini Dragons so to speak. I’m actually pretty sure they will do it. Refueling satellites on orbit would be probably too complex as there are so many in different planes and they also can’t really upgrade them like that. But if they decide to do that the next problem will be catching them. That’s a 1000 satellites. (www.kNews.space) How could they possibly prevent them to fall into the water? First of all SpaceX is incredibly good at aiming as they do it on their Dragon all the time. So I’m sure they could re-enter aim for somewhere near the west coast. Second, they could not use drone ships but regular flying drones. There is an older video linked below where you can see how students or graduates, I’m not sure, built software that can control a team of drones catching a ball using a net inflight. That’s crazy but I think just the right way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_004/04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Catching Satellites using Drones&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Steven who usually catches fairings could harbor some car sized drones that would do exactly that. Catch satellites. This could even turn into a fully autonomous launch and catch cycle. Drones catch the satellites, bring them to the rocket where they gets refueled and relaunched. Isn’t it a good idea to build a self maintaining satellite fleet that offers communication, possibly positioning to autonomous vehicles all around the globe? Hmmm wait a second… that reminds me of the documentary.. what was its name again? &lt;em&gt;drum noise&lt;/em&gt; The Terminator. But jokes aside, what do you think guys? The Skynet comparison is surely a little exaggerated but do you believe they could disrupt yet another industry with reusable satellites or am I nuts? Do you have some cool ideas what Starlink could else be used for?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="spacex" /><category term="starlink" /><category term="explained" /><category term="how" /><summary type="html">The dotted white outer rim to the sides shows regular communication satellites in a geosynchronous orbit. There are roughly 500 or these currently in orbit and most of you will know them from satellite television. Yep, that’s where you point your dishes at. The ISS orbits much more closely at 400 km, in fact it’s so close you wouldn’t even notice its in space at all from up here. The red dot zips across the sky at 8 km/s in order to not fall back to ground. It counters gravity with its own inertia like a giant centrifuge.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%222018/vlog_004_spacex-starlink.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Dangerous are Black Holes?</title><link href="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/how-dangerous-black-holes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Dangerous are Black Holes?" /><published>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/how-dangerous-black-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/how-dangerous-black-holes.html">&lt;p&gt;Black Holes are among the most mysterious objects in the sky but, how dangerous are they? I want to explore this question in this logbook entry and give you are quick summary of how I understand the topic. Please be aware that I’m not an astrophysicist and can only share my view which may have som flaws! My main inspiration is the thought of such a hole flying by our sun! I never really thought about how dangerous this seemingly innocent event could be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all I find the name black hole a little misleading but it got stuck for what is essentially a black star. A star forms from collapsing gas clouds in space very similar to gas giants like Jupiter. What you see in the video above is a litte simulation I wrote based on Newtonian physics and this shall just prove that all animations - with the simulation icon to the lower right - are NOT just made up but act very similar if not identical to real planets and stars. I could in fact never control the movements of so many objects by hand and if you are still sceptical you can of course look for errors in some of the celestial body movements. They are all equal in mass and occupy a region that is roughly as big as our inner solar system. Back at a star formation the amount of gas collapsing into a single object is much bigger than that of a gas giant so that the star generates enough pressure in its core for fusion to begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_003/01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;n-body Simulation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusing atom cores or nuclei together requires immense forces because they repel each other as they are made of Protons and Neutrons and are therefore positively charged. Once they get close enough though, other forces that keep the Protons themselves holding together take over and the two cores snap together rapidly as if a barrier was crushed. Depending on what elements fuse this process releases a lot of energy which heats up the star’s core to many many millions of degrees Celcius. (www.kNews.space) Life would actually be impossible near any star if there wasn’t that thousands of kilometers thick gas cloud covering the hot inner regions, which is also necessary to generate that pressure in first place. So we don’t have to fear that this cloud could be blown away off our sun anytime soon since the star would not be able to sustain such a strong fusion without it. But, at some point, as a star’s fusion gets more intense with age, the core temperature gets hotter and hotter fusing elements together even at the most outer layers. This is where a star blows up to many times its size until its core extinguishes causing the entire star to collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This collapse or implosion causes some massive star clouds to bounce back exploding into outer space, a supernova. It spreads the new elements it created around the galaxy causing nearby gas clouds to collapse in a billion year chain reaction forming new stars and systems as the universe ages. Just btw. a supernova, while similar, is not directly related to a nova. The terms got a little mixed up right there since a regular nova is a star explosion caused by one star feeding from another, and not one star blowing up on its own. Anyways, the remains most commonly shrink forming a white or black dwarf star. For extremely massive stars however, this is where it gets really interesting. The dwarf they leave behind ia a Neutron Star where you couldn’t lift a single scoop of matter with the strongest of machines. A cubic meter has a mass of millions of tons. Unimaginably heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_003/02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Neutron Star Comparison&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a Neutron Star is the only glimpse we have at the formation of black holes. They are essentially the last step before matter collapses into the abyss. Into nothing, a single point with zero space, the famous singularity. Full disclosure, I’m not a physicist, but to get an idea how this is possible at all one has to know that the size of matter as we know it, is only based on the fundamental forces of nature. A solid surface looks solid to us because of the way light bounces of it and it feels solid because of how the surface atoms interact with our body’s. We can’t push our hand through it because there is a force stopping us. And it is nothing but a force. The force is strong in that one. Given enough pressure you could push your hand through everything assuming that the force would not crush the hand itself. What I try to say is even the smallest of elements that take up a certain space do that based on these strange forces, that just exist with yet unknown origin. (www.kNews.space) This hopefully helps to illustrate that when the outside pressure caused my gravity wins, they can collapse indefinitely like the hand moved through the wall. There is no known boundary or limit to how small matter or energy can be compressed by gravity. Thinking about black holes it is therefore important to know that these are giant stars, carrying the same mass, just collapsed into spaces so small that we cannot see them anymore. What we instead see or not s…not observe, is a region surrounding them where the gravity gets so intense that everything that falls behind it is trapped forever, even light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance from the singularity where this region begins is the so called Schwarzschild or Schwarzschild radius and it can range from just a few kilometers for small black holes up to millions of kilometers for supermassive ones like the one holding our galaxy together in the center of our milky way. The literal translation of Schwarzschild from German btw. is Black Shield Radius which is ironically quite fitting. However, it is actually a German astrophysicist’s name: Karl Schwarzschild. So it’s not a term you would translate. While the inner workings of a black hole are unknown and matter of speculation, everything outside the Schwarzschild-Radius is very well understood. The gravity of a black hole is not different to that of stars and other bodies even ourselves. The black hole in our galaxy’s center is not sucking up the galaxy as one would maybe imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tens of billions of stars just orbit itmon peaceful and stable trajectories like our solar system does for now billions of years with a couple dozen rounds trips so far. The dangerous black holes I want to talk about are not the giant ones in the centers of galaxies. I want to talk about relatively small rogue black holes that zip around the milky way like our sun does. Unlike our sun they are invisible and they can only be observed indirectly by either a glowing disc of matter surrounding them, or the warp in spacetime they create. Gravity warps space time forming a giant 3-dimensional funnel a little like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This funnel is the reason for why we are glued to our planet’s surface and don’t fall off into space. So keeping track and mapping the 3D space of our surrounding stars is therefore vital to find such rogue black holes. The danger does not lie in the black hole itself though. At least according to my simulations. A direct hit with our sun or our earth is very unlikely due to their incredibly small size but that doesn’t means its harmless. Our solar system balanced itself out of billions of years and is much more fragile that one would imagine. (ww w.kN ews.spac e) To illustrate this I can again use my little simulation tool and plug in the numbers for our solar system. It now shows how the real orbiting bodies would be affected by a flyby of the most lightest of black holes, just a couple times heavier than our sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera is locked to the sun so the point it leaves behind is its origin as it gets attracted towards the incoming threat. And here it comes from the top. Woah. It really scared the hell out of me when I saw this. I never really thought about the dangers of just a seemingly innocent flyby. The black hole would fling most of the solar system’s planets into deep space and separate us from our host star or as seen here throw us directly into it. Our future friends on Mars are not much better off. I simulated it hundreds of years into the future at it will end up crashing into the sun as well as Jupiter gives it its final gravity assist. This means just moving to a neighbouring planet is not the final solution to safe humanity and possibly life for an eternity. We have to move out to different stars in the long run if we want to sustain us and our surroundings. But falling into the sun has actually a rather low chance and I use this for the dramatic effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/2018/vlog_003/03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Hole Slingshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The by far most common outcome in all the simulations I ran is a slingshot into deep space. Black holes are multiple times more heavy than our sun so such slingshots are incredibly powerful. Now, I don’t want to leave you worrying about such a dark future. We as humans are thankfully very good at dealing with never before seen problems and science will allow us to identify such threats long before they actually put our lifes at risk. We would become the Guardians of the Earth as we’d use our knowledge of fusion power to create our own sun. Or multiple ones! Double sun power!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But seriously, we could fuse hydrogen like the sun does to warm up the planet even without a star so I am very positive that even such a worst case scenario would not be the end of all life as we know it. The foundations to this are currently laid at many places and one of them is ITER or International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor. (www.kNews.space) The biggest ever experimental fusion reactor that is supposed to generate power is being built in europe as I speak. But the first step would probably be to seek shelter below the ground to make use of our own planet’s heat source, the by nuclear fission driven thermal activities deep down below the earth’s crust. For that we’d need boring machines and what not which is of course also being worked on, but that’s maybe a story for another video. Have you ever thought about black holes flying by our sun? Tell me what you think!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="black hole" /><category term="danger" /><category term="cosmos" /><category term="solar system" /><summary type="html">Black Holes are among the most mysterious objects in the sky but, how dangerous are they? I want to explore this question in this logbook entry and give you are quick summary of how I understand the topic. Please be aware that I’m not an astrophysicist and can only share my view which may have som flaws! My main inspiration is the thought of such a hole flying by our sun! I never really thought about how dangerous this seemingly innocent event could be?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%222018/vlog_003_black-hole-danger.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX Second Stage Reuse!</title><link href="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-falcon-second-stage-reuse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX Second Stage Reuse!" /><published>2018-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-falcon-second-stage-reuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-falcon-second-stage-reuse.html">&lt;p&gt;This logbook entry is about Falcon’s not yet but hopefully soon reusable upper stage. As every space enthusiast is aware of, SpaceX is recovering and reusing their first stage boosters. The first stage turns around and guides itself like a missile after separation, using grid fins to hit its target drone ship out in the ocean. Then, just before impact, up to three engines ignite to land on the floating platform which is stabilized and held in place by the ship’s extremely powerful and foldable propellers. This still one of a kind maneuver is what makes SpaceX so different from other rocket companies which all throw away their boosters crashing them into the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having figured out how to land the booster safely SpaceX also decided to recover their multi million dollar payload fairing. While it looks simple this fairing pushes against all the aerodynamic pressure during launch to protect the payload up top. It’s normally separated once the rocket leaves the atmosphere to then also crash into the ocean. A rather simple solution SpaceX came up with is to equip each of the fairing halves with a parafoil and cold gas thrusters. The thrust keeps them oriented and stable while they re-enter back into the atmosphere before the parafoil is released. Operating a parafoil above such a giant piece of hardware is extremely challenging due to all the turbulences and SpaceX is yet not able to land land their fairings routinely but they’re of course working on it. Each half is supposed to land on a second ship out in the ocean called Mr. Steven. It has a giant net stretched over four enormous pillars and I assume they will have two of those ships in the future. (www.kNews.space) That’s what Elon Musk refers to as a bouncy castle btw.. It’s bouncy but castle mmh not so much but let’s not start to nitpick here because there will probably be no party balloons recovering the upper stage either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-far-so-good&quot;&gt;So far so good..&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of the rocket that remains crashing into the ocean is that upper stage. Recovering and reusing it has not the highest priority for SpaceX since they are working on their next gen rocket, the BFR, which stands for. It’s the Big F***on Rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, they are going to try it, improving it progressively. Similar to the fairings the upper stage is supposed to land on a ship probably also using a parafoil of some sort only bigger. The most difficult part though is to re-enter back into the atmosphere without breaking up which is a completely different endeavour flying at orbital speeds. One important thing to keep in mind is every kilogram added to the upper stage means a kilogram less payload since the upper stage goes wherever the payload goes naturally. So I assume this is only an option for either light Falcon 9 payloads or the Falcon Heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;balloon--parachute--ballute&quot;&gt;Balloon + Parachute = Ballute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most popular method on the internet to get the upper stage back is a so called ballute. Not that balut guys from the philippines. This one is a fusion between a balloon and a parachute. Ha! It inflates itself like a parachute without the need of any gas while providing a huge surface area to act as a giant drag brake essentially. The idea is to decrease the speed as fast as possible during reentry and keep the nose of the stage pointing downward. (ww w.kN ews.spac e) Without it the heaviest part would face the hot plasma which would be the engine section. It could then double to either land the upper stage safely on a ship, or maybe even allow to catch it with a giant drone like the United Launch Alliance plans to do with their Vulcan rocket’s engine section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, latter sounds a little too complex for SpaceX as this recovery is not a priority right now. But who knows. I’m not quite sure how all of that would work out especially since the ballute had to be heat resistant. But that’s just one way they could do it and I want to explore a more crazy method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the ballute idea sounds really good and was even tried before, I’m still a bit sceptical about this approach. The reason is it can only be used during reentry and they couldn’t deorbit and lose speed before that happens. Such a ballute also had to be mounted next to the engine which could have unknown consequences to a launch and I doubt they will do a test launch with it or recertify their upper stage. Mounting inflatable stuff as a secondary payload inside the fairing on the other hand should be no big deal. So I think they will at least start putting stuff there to gain experience before they make changes in more dangerous areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-save-the-engine&quot;&gt;How to save the engine?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what could they do in order to reenter without destroying the expensive engine? The solution is to get rid of as much speed as possible while still in space. It’s of course highly speculative at this point but the upper stage tanks are pressurized with Helium gas as they drain. Once the mission is over this gas is vented into space to make sure the upper stage tanks do not rupture from heating up in the sunlight. As you can imagine this gas could also be used to inflate a giant balloon. (www.kNews.space) To make things a little less complicated and stable SpaceX could omit the rope and mount the balloon or multiple balloons directly to the payload adapter. However, doing it like this they had to mount a pipe at the side of the vehicle since all the necessary connections are at the bottom where the engine is. I’m not sure if SpaceX is willing to do changes to its fuel piping system to reuse the upper stage but for this video I assume they do. If not it’s probably going to be a self inflating ballute as mentioned in the beginning that does not require internal gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A benefit of such side mounted balloons would be they could act like giant inflatable fins basically. Varying the pressure and size they could even steer the upper stage and point the bottom section in the right direction to bounce off the atmosphere a little like the Space Shuttle used to do in order to lose as much velocity as possible before they hit the thicker more dense layers where the real heating begins. (www.kNews.space) Whatever they come up with and which orientation the upper stage will reenter, they will not be able to get rid of all the velocity so some kind of heat shield will be needed. SpaceX plan is to add more and more insulation to its upper stage similar to what they’ve done to their Block 5 booster. They covered all the parts that are exposed to the reentry heat with their black insulating material. They will either shield more of the engine or come up with a payload adapter shielding solution, where they can still mount the payload safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though, I personally only see it as a backup plan should the development of BFR not go as smoothly and take much longer than expected. Having a completely reusable rocket would make a big difference and would drop the costs to launch Falcon down to single digit million values competing with even the smallest of launchers. Even if it was Falcon Heavy. Do you have some thoughts on it as well? Feel free to leave a comment below the video I read all of them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="spacex" /><category term="falcon9" /><category term="reuse" /><category term="upper stage" /><summary type="html">This logbook entry is about Falcon’s not yet but hopefully soon reusable upper stage. As every space enthusiast is aware of, SpaceX is recovering and reusing their first stage boosters. The first stage turns around and guides itself like a missile after separation, using grid fins to hit its target drone ship out in the ocean. Then, just before impact, up to three engines ignite to land on the floating platform which is stabilized and held in place by the ship’s extremely powerful and foldable propellers. This still one of a kind maneuver is what makes SpaceX so different from other rocket companies which all throw away their boosters crashing them into the ocean.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%222018/vlog_002_spacex-second-stage.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX BFR Issues Explained!</title><link href="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-bfr-issues-explained.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX BFR Issues Explained!" /><published>2017-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-10-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-bfr-issues-explained</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-bfr-issues-explained.html">&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk recently unveiled SpaceX new BFR design to bring humans to Mars and how to fund  it. In this logbook entry I want to share my thoughts on 3 commonly pointed out issues which raise a lot of questions. You are of course free to share your view and I’m looking forward to some debates!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issue-number-1&quot;&gt;Issue Number 1:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SpaceShip is too small to fit 100 people comfortably for weeks and months flying to Mars. SpaceX slides show that the spaceship will feature 825 m³ of pressurized space. Compare that to the 910 m³ of the ISS and you might wonder: How on earth should 100 people feel comfortable in the same space 6 astronauts do on the ISS? That’s a valid point but the first thing to point out here is the ISS internal volume is stuffed with all sorts of cargo, experiments and hardware. The volume in which the astronauts can roam around is smaller than 910 m³. By how much I’m not entirely sure about but it is a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you a better feel for the stations total volume it would be comparable to a big 2 by 3 meter service elevator in a 50 story building standing 150 meters tall. Spreading 100 people evenly across all floors you’d end up with 2 astronauts sharing the space of such a service elevator. Now that feels like not that much space but you also have to keep in mind people going to mars would do shifts. For example: One third would be sleeping packed together tightly, another third could be working on computers to maybe even make some money on the way to Mars and the last third would enjoy their free time with a lot more space per person than the 2/3rds below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now of course you could say w-w-w-wait, the spaceship is packed with cargo for Mars as well. However, as you can see here, the cone has a volume of 825 m³ and it looks like this is the pressurized free space available for crew, not including the areas you can see the cargo bags on SpaceX image. (www.kNews.space) That’s why in my opinion there is plenty space on board and technology like Virtual Reality will only further help to feel comfortable and also private. Putting on your glasses and headphones you can visit places you always wanted to like a holodeck and we’re only at the beginning of that! The further technology advances the more immersive it will feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issue-number-2&quot;&gt;Issue Number 2:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BFR is too expensive to replace F9 and Falcon Heavy for smaller payloads. Putting F9, Falcon Heavy and BFR side by side makes it look ridiculous to launch similar satellites to GTO using SpaceX giant rocket. It can lift 150 tons to low earth orbit which means you would waste a lot of capability burning way too much fuel, rendering it just too expensive to launch small payloads. However, here is where the so called paradigm shift happens. Although F9 and Falcon Heavy are partly reusable, you still lose the entire upper stage for every payload you launch to orbit. The upper stages cost is something you always have to add on top. The price to build an upper stage s higher than the cost to refuel the BFR. Now I don’t have the exact numbers but I can give you a ballpark number. Falcons upper stage costs in the order of 20 million dollars while the amount of fuel necessary to fill a cylinder the size of BFR, would cost less than a tenth of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown in the presentation launching a satellite using BFR would not only be cheaper than using Falcon 9, it would also underbid Falcon 1 and probably any other expendable rocket on the market today or in the near future. No matter how small they are they always cost a couple millions. But of course, BFR will not want to launch with a single 50 kg satellite on board so the way in which payloads are assigned to launch vehicles has to also change drastically in order to fill up such a big rocket. But still, it is important to keep in mind even launching a single small satellite would be worth it. Now this is all theory. (ww w.kNe ws.spa ce) In reality SpaceX also wants to earn money in order to fund their Mars project and that means as long as the competition is unable to follow their price drop they could have huge margins. These margins would allow them to build all sorts of crazy things which leads me to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issue-number-3&quot;&gt;Issue Number 3:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching rockets for point to point transport on earth is expensive and pollutes the environment. The short video SpaceX has shown makes it seem quite ridiculous to travel using rockets. I have to admit, when I saw it, I first thought it would be more of a funny joke. But then I thought of companies which launch tourists on suborbital flights to space. It’s essentially the same just instead of 5 minutes of weightlessness you’d hover for up to 30 minutes while at the same time traveling to other continents. The payload capacity of 150 tons to low earth orbit means you could easily transport 1000 people at once if you’d manage to fit them inside the vehicle. Not too unrealistic considering you’d need no crew supplies as you’d if you went to orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming fuel costs of one million dollars it would be 1000$ per average ticket whereas other suborbital flights are expected to cost a 100 times more. 1000$ is a lot of money but to experience space for half an hour? I think many would save their money just for that experience. But of course, economics also apply here so they would charge as much as the customers are willing to pay for. Some seats with big windows would cost more, others without windows less. (www.kNews.space) But what about the environment and all the pollution from dozens of rockets launching per day? Going to Mars SpaceX will have to develop a system to produce fuel to return the ship back to earth. This system has to be tested here on earth and I personally speculate that they will at least fill up one rocket to show that it works. Propellant made out of water and air is environmentally neutral. This means all the CO2 released from a rocket was taken out of the atmosphere to create the propellant in first place. So there would be no pollution as long as SpaceX would use propellant they made on their own. It would be more expensive than to instead sell the electric energy and buy cheap fossil fuel but considering the big advantage from full reusability and the relatively small fuel cost I’d say it’s not entirely out of question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that they have spent money to produce free fuel why turn the machine off? At some point these factories had generated so much free propellant that they would have amortized their initial cost. Once you are at this point were propellant is really free, BFR could also easily compete with jet airplanes when it comes transportation as shown in the video. (www.kNews.space) Now this would of course take many years but I personally see no reason why it couldn’t happen from an economics standpoint but I’m not really a pro at economics so feel free to correct me on that! Important to note is, SpaceX will make a lot of money if they succeed to build a fully reusable rocket before anyone else does. They would be able outbid anyone and pretty much decide which other launch provider would get to launch some payload and which not. To quote Spiderman’s uncle: “With great power comes great responsibility”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some disruptive times ahead and I’m curious to know your stance on that! How do you think will the aerospace industry have to chance in order to stay competitive? Is it enough to build cheaper yet still expendable rockets or do you think everyone has to switch to full reusability asap?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="spacex" /><category term="bfr" /><summary type="html">Elon Musk recently unveiled SpaceX new BFR design to bring humans to Mars and how to fund it. In this logbook entry I want to share my thoughts on 3 commonly pointed out issues which raise a lot of questions. You are of course free to share your view and I’m looking forward to some debates!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://blog.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%222017/vlog_001_spacex-bfr.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry></feed>