<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.knews.space/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.knews.space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-20T13:14:47+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/</id><title type="html">kNews Space</title><subtitle>Rocket Launch and Space News</subtitle><author><name>Lukas</name></author><entry><title type="html">Blue Origin’s New Shepard launched secretly!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blue Origin’s New Shepard launched secretly! " /><published>2017-12-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0.html">&lt;p&gt;Blue Origin’s New Shepard rocket shot their brand new “Crew Capsule 2.0” into a sub orbital trajectory above the Mojave desert. This happened on December 12th 2017 and was as far as I know not streamed live nor announced, so I call it secret! Blue Origin was founded by Jeff Bezos who is also the head at the e-commerce giant amazon. Next to New Shepard, Blue Origin is also working on its orbital class launch vehicle called New Glenn which will use 7 BE-4 engines burning liquid methane and oxygen on its first stage, unlike New Shepard which burns liquid Hydrogen. However, New Shepard’s BE-3 engine will probably be used on an expendable third stage of the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Shepard seems to have been upgraded being called the “next generation booster” and the capsule now finally features real windows - which were previously only painted on. Shooting the capsule straight up it almost passed the Karman line at 99 km at its highest point - the Apoapsis. This was therefore strictly speaking not a “space flight” but it doesn’t really make a difference to the payload whether you cross 100 km or not. The border of 100 km arises from aviation where a plane traveling at this altitude had to reach orbital velocity in order to gain enough lift from its wings to stay up. This is because of the extremely low, yet existing air pressure and means wings are not needed anymore once above orbital velocity and 100 km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both capsule and booster landed successfully afterwards and New Shepard once again delivered a pinpoint arrival on its landing area, which by the way got a new paint job. It could be similar to SpaceX’ one a more radar reflective material to enhance the accuracy, which could also double as a more durable coating to the extremely hot exhaust gas. However, that’s just speculation on my end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onboard Crew Capsule 2.0 was no crew but not further specified commercial, educational and research equipment. On suborbital parabolic flights like these cargo still experiences weightlessness for a few seconds to minutes, which is enough time to perform many different experiments that are just better suited for free fall. An example for this would be the ice crystal formation in clouds. Watching droplets freeze in mid air is very hard to achieve in the lab. You can of course watch entire steam clouds freezing but individual particles not so much. In such a free fall environment on the other hand you can make droplets hover just in front a microscope to observe how they form to gain a better understanding of what is actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the below linked video carefully you will also notice different reflective properties on the capsule windows. Some are highly reflective like chrome while others look much more see-through and dark. The purpose is unknown at the moment but could either be related to the experiments hiding behind them, or Blue Origin could be testing different window materials to figure out what is best for its future tourists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The radiation especially in the Ultraviolet range (UV) is extremely high above the atmosphere and potential tourist eyes have to be protected from that. Adding reflective coating is not hard but comes with the big downside of also reflecting visible light you want to enjoy during flight coming off of earth. It would definitely lower the overall experience if everything would look like you’d watch through extremely dark sunglasses. The future will tell what Blue Origin will come up with but I’m positive they will figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ZJghIk7_VA&quot; class=&quot;inverted&quot;&gt;Mannequin Skywalker’s Ride to Space&lt;/a&gt; by Blue Origin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="november" /><category term="2017" /><category term="Blue-Origin" /><category term="New-Shepard" /><category term="Jeff-Bezos" /><category term="Crew-Capsule-2.0" /><summary type="html">Blue Origin’s New Shepard rocket shot their brand new “Crew Capsule 2.0” into a sub orbital trajectory above the Mojave desert. This happened on December 12th 2017 and was as far as I know not streamed live nor announced, so I call it secret! Blue Origin was founded by Jeff Bezos who is also the head at the e-commerce giant amazon. Next to New Shepard, Blue Origin is also working on its orbital class launch vehicle called New Glenn which will use 7 BE-4 engines burning liquid methane and oxygen on its first stage, unlike New Shepard which burns liquid Hydrogen. However, New Shepard’s BE-3 engine will probably be used on an expendable third stage of the rocket.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22004_New-Shepard-Crew-Capsule.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Astronauts and 4 Rockets Launch!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Astronauts and 4 Rockets Launch!" /><published>2017-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 50/2017 I mainly talk about the upcoming Soyuz launch to the ISS carrying three astronauts, but I also mention three other launches namely: Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9 and Arianespace’s Ariane 5!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/17): To round off the week Soyuz brought its astronauts to space safely. The Soyuz spacecraft will dock to the station on Tuesday December 19th which is the long track to the ISS. I’m not entirely sure why they chose this longer profile but it might be due to SpaceX’s Dragon capsule which arrived on Sunday. However, it could also be the other way around so that Dragon was allowed to launch just because Soyuz would chose the longer profile. Either way, best luck to those astronauts sitting in their tin can far above the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/16): Rocket Lab decided to give their staff some rest and push their Electron launch into 2018 due to some issues with the rocket and the weather. Better safe than sorry I would say.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/15): SpaceX Falcon 9 had a successful launch delivering Dragon into a low earth orbit while landing its booster at Landing Zone 1. There is only one launch left this year for SpaceX which will take place in Vanderberg. Should this one succeed SpaceX will leave 2017 with a perfect flight record without a failure. That’s not as self-evident as it might seem because SpaceX are constantly changing their hardware releasing new version of their boosters frequently. This year we moved from Block 3 to Block 4 while the final Block 5 is just around the corner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/13): Ariane 5 brought its 4 passengers named Nicole, Zofia, Alexandre and Irina (drawing competition winners) into their desired circular medium earth orbits. They will now individually raise their trajectory over the course of several weeks until they can be put into service at their constellation slots. Adding 4 satellites will enhance the accuracy and availability of the GALILEO navigation system because more satellites means the chance to have some of them in the sky above is higher. It takes 4 to determine a location successfully but the more the better. Congratulations to Arianespace and ESA!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three astronauts go to space and four rockets launch, now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here welcome to kNews for week 50 and as always a big shout out to my kNews boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I come to the launches I want to announce some changes to kNews. I used to try push out one video per week covering all the launches in great detail, which to be honest, is just too much. I tried to be fair and treat all payloads and rockets the same but even I have to say communication satellite number 105 is just not as exciting to talk about even though every rocket launch is cool to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to pick out one topic per week which I will put my heart and soul into while only mentioning all the upcoming launches briefly in the beginning. Now, this is all not set in stone and I will listen to your feedback on that carefully to make some adjustments. The topic I focus on could be a particular launch but it could also be something else like a Special episode. My main goal is to release one episode per week consistently which I still fail to deliver very often. Anyways, let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching this week are Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9, Ariane 5 and a Soyuz. Three of them might actually launch on the same day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up is Electron which has a rather loose schedule. It could launch any day of the week at 1:30 UTC from the Rocket Lab Launch Complex 1 in New Zealand. The main constraint is the weather I believe. Up top are 4 Cubesats, two of each from type Flock-2 and Lemur-2. All these are equipped with cameras to take picture from the ground below and are part of large Cubesat constellation belonging to the companies Planet Labs and Spire Global.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is a SpaceX Falcon 9 with an inaugural flight from Space Launch Complex 40 on Tuesday at 16:46 UTC. The launch pad bas broken due to a Falcon 9 exploding last year but it’s back. This means the other pad 39 can be finally changed to support Falcon Heavy. Up top Falcon 9 is a Dragon 1 spacecraft filled with cargo for the International Space Station. To get there it will be shot into a low earth orbit inclined at 51.6 degrees. The same one the ISS is orbiting at but of course just a little lower to catch up with it. A special thing to mention here is the booster and the capsule are both flight proven as SpaceX is referring to their reused hardware. The turnaround time is still very high but Block 5, the final iteration of Falcon 9, is not yet flying. Block 5 will include a lot of changes which make reusing the booster easier to finally step up the re-launch game to ultimately increase the launch cadence immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number three on the list is an Ariane 5 hopefully causing a rumble in the jungle on Tuesday as well at 18:36 UTC in Kourou, French Guiana. Up top are two GALILEO navigation satellites which will be shot into a 56 degrees inclined transfer orbit. Their destination is one of three medium earth orbital planes with an altitude of roundabout 22,000 km. The navigation constellation is not yet finished and Arianespace will continue to build it up for the european union to be a little more independent from the US GPS and Russia’s GLONASS which are quite similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last launch this week aims for the International Space Station as well but that one is filled with astronauts so I will of course feature it in greater detail. It’s a Soyuz rocket currently scheduled to lift off on Sunday at 07:21 UTC from Baikonur in Kazakhstan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top the Soyuz rocket is the Soyuz spacecraft hiding behind a tight fairing. The pointy tower up top is the escape system which is basically a solid fueled booster firing its engines to the sides should something go wrong. It would separate the crew from the rocket in the early stages of the flight. However, it will be staged away mid flight once the rocket is in space to get rid of the weight since the spacecraft could separate from the rocket on its own should its engines fail. The escape system is also only designed for an in-atmospheric abort using grid fins to steer it at high speeds. This wouldn’t work in space and an abort so late into the mission could cause the capsule to tumble and spin uncontrollably. This would be very dangerous and life threatening for the astronauts on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned Soyuz will launch from Baikonur and head north east to follow an inclination of 51.6 degrees. As it speeds into the sky its flight computer will do most of the work and drop its empty stages on the way up. Since these empty tanks drop on ground Roscosmos actually has a ground crew to locate the crash sites and return the boosters. I’m not sure what they do with them but I guess there are some valuable materials on that rocket which could be recycled into new rockets. However, that’s just my speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rocket heads up in the background let me introduce to you the astronauts joining Expedition 54 on the ISS. For Russia we have Anton Shkaplerov. He is 45 years old and was born in Ukraine. His career started as a Russian Air Force pilot and he later on graduated in Air Force Engineering. So far Anton has spent a year in space and by a year I really mean 365 days to be precise. Ahem, he was twice aboard the station already once in 2012 and once in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is Kanai Norishige from Japan. He turns 41 this month and is a military doctor who did specialise in surgery I think. He later transferred to the Japan Self Defense Force Hospital in Kure which lies in the Hiroshima district of Japan. There he become a Diving Medical Officer after he has qualified himself as a diver in the US Navy. This will be his first flight to space where his diving experience could really pay off but I’m not sure if he will participate in any extravehicular activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally on board is also an US astronaut namely Scott Manley, err, I mean Scott Tingle. He is 52 years old and was born in Attleboro, Massachusetts. This gotta be one of the hardest to pronounce english words. Holy moly. Massachusetts. Anyways, Scott’s career is also dominated by military service as most astronauts. He is a commander in the US Navy and a test pilot. This will be also he first mission to space after he has qualified as an astronaut in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish these brave astronauts all the best luck on their ride to the station and of course also a nice christmas and new years eve they will share with the other crew members awaiting their arrival on the ISS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. This show is mainly supported by crowdfunding so please consider to become a kNews Booster if you can spare a dollar or two. I’m currently saving for better hardware to render all those animations you see more quickly. Again big thanks to all who have supported me so far. Auf Wiedersehn and Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2017" /><category term="spacex" /><category term="falcon-9" /><category term="soyuz" /><category term="ariane-5" /><category term="rocket-lab" /><category term="Electron" /><category term="50-2017" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 50/2017 I mainly talk about the upcoming Soyuz launch to the ISS carrying three astronauts, but I also mention three other launches namely: Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9 and Arianespace’s Ariane 5!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_502017.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX to Launch Tesla Roadster to Mars</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX to Launch Tesla Roadster to Mars" /><published>2017-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space.html">&lt;p&gt;Yep, it’s not a joke (as it seems). SpaceX’ Falcon Heavy will launch Elon Musk’s red Tesla Roaster to Mars on its maiden flight in January 2018 according to a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/936782477502246912&quot;&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt;. My illustration up top shows a Tesla Model X because this is the only one I got modeled in 3D which I used in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fYuvOMnDRdc&quot;&gt;Tesla Project Loveday&lt;/a&gt;” entry. However, it is still unclear whether it will be one of the new 200 kWh Roadsters which will arrive at the market by 2020, or one if not the first Tesla Roadster Elon Musk ever owned himself. This would be quite emotional and a real loss for him should something go wrong! &lt;em&gt;knocks on wood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.knews.space/assets/img/003_Musk-Tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elon Musk Tweet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Falcon Heavy is SpaceX’ yet heaviest and most powerful rocket to fly. Due to unexpected difficulties when it comes to “simply strapping more Falcon boosters to Falcon 9”, the maiden flight was delayed back multiple times. It was first accounced to fly in 2012 which was of course a very optimistic timeframe to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in space and separated from the rocket, the Tesla Roadster will coast to Mars and do a close flyby performing a swing-by or gravity assist around the red planet. Due to the lack of propulsion the Roadster will not be able to enter into a stable orbit and will instead be shot into outter space maybe even visiting other planets. However, this is just my speculation because no further details have been published yet. It’s unlikely that SpaceX would build a full-fledged spacecraft around the Roadster though. I assume attachments will mostly consist of solar panels, cameras and communication equiptment to send its data back to earth. A gyroscope or some cold gas thrusters would also make sense to change its orientation and maybe some basic radiators to keep its batteries cool. But who knows, maybe I’m completely wrong and they will turn the Roadster into Lone Starr’s Eagle 5. &amp;amp;128526;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its journey it will of course take a lot of images like selfies from itself and Mars and maybe Phobos or Deimos too - Mars’ moons. What seems rediculous is actually just part of a very risky test flight. Elon Musk himself said, he would consider it a “win” if the rocket clears the towers and does not cause any damage to the launch site. Other rockets often also use so called dummy payloads on test flights but these are of course usually much less exciting or at least not further detailed. There could be a lot cool and silly stuff in space we don’t know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Falcon Heavy ignites 27 Merlin engines during launch which all shoot out their exhaust gases at speeds above the speed of sound. This leads to shock waves forming similar to sonic booms which not only hit the ground, but also reflect back at the vehicle making it hard to predict if everything will go well. SpaceX uses water cannons to fill the air with tiny droplets absorbing hopefully enough of the shock wave’s energy to keep dangerous oscillations away from Falcon Heavy’s highly pressurized body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.knews.space/assets/img/003_falcon-heavy-exhaust.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Falcon Heavy Exhaust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally think this is a brilliant marketing move - even if it’s not intented to be one - and might open up space to much more then just “rational” payloads. A Falcon Heavy is able to shoot 17 metric tons of payload to Mars in its expendable setup, maybe half of that as a reuseable rocket which would be still enough to shoot hundreds of mummified human remains to the red planet. Humanity would finally fulfill its dream to rest in peace among the stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dec. 3rd: There is some new information about the story not being true and made up by Elon Musk, but these don’t refer to official tweets just a talk between Musk and TheVerge. Knowing Musk’s sense of humor a little I personally think he would rather troll TheVerge than to admit lying. At this point if it was indeed a joke it would be a toy Tesla glued to the payload playing music. That would still be a Tesla flying to Mars. Future will tell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dec. 2nd: I just noticed Elon Musk answered a question about the model of the car in the comments below his tweet. It will be a first generation Tesla Roadster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="november" /><category term="2017" /><category term="SpaceX" /><category term="Falcon-Heavy" /><category term="Mars" /><category term="Tesla" /><category term="Elon-Musk" /><summary type="html">Yep, it’s not a joke (as it seems). SpaceX’ Falcon Heavy will launch Elon Musk’s red Tesla Roaster to Mars on its maiden flight in January 2018 according to a tweet by Elon Musk. My illustration up top shows a Tesla Model X because this is the only one I got modeled in 3D which I used in my Tesla Project Loveday” entry. However, it is still unclear whether it will be one of the new 200 kWh Roadsters which will arrive at the market by 2020, or one if not the first Tesla Roadster Elon Musk ever owned himself. This would be quite emotional and a real loss for him should something go wrong! knocks on wood</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22003_SpaceX-Falcon9-Tesla.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Soyuz’s Fregat Upper Stage Burned Up!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/Soyuz-Reentry-Anomaly-Failure-Fregat-Meteor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Soyuz's Fregat Upper Stage Burned Up!" /><published>2017-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/Soyuz-Reentry-Anomaly-Failure-Fregat-Meteor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/Soyuz-Reentry-Anomaly-Failure-Fregat-Meteor.html">&lt;p&gt;Sad news from Russia. The recently launched Soyuz - which I covered a little prematurely in kNews for week 46/2017, has had an anomaly on its Fregat (frigate) upper stage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nominal-then-boom&quot;&gt;Nominal then Boom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a nominal launch from the new Vostochny Cosmodrome in eastern Russia, Fregat was supposed to boost its payload, a Meteor-M satellite, into its desired polar orbit. According to RussiaSpaceWeb the guidance computer believed it would launch from the older Plesetsk Cosmodrome near Moscow, Russia’s capital, or Baikonur in Kazakhstan. This led to an unplanned course correction by the flight computer followed by a wrong thrust vector. The upper stage then inevitably re-entered back into the atmosphere because it didn’t pick up enough speed to circumvent the globe in a stable orbit. The energetic event was observed by people on the other side of the globe and shows us once again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Space is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.russianspaceweb.com/meteor-m2-1.html&quot;&gt;Article on RussiaSpaceWeb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="november" /><category term="2017" /><category term="soyuz" /><category term="failure" /><category term="anomaly" /><category term="fregat" /><category term="reentry" /><summary type="html">Sad news from Russia. The recently launched Soyuz - which I covered a little prematurely in kNews for week 46/2017, has had an anomaly on its Fregat (frigate) upper stage!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22002_soyuz-failure-anomaly-reentry-november-2017-meteor.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">6 + 2C + 3B*? = Chinese (中文) Launch Week</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Long-March-6-2C-3B-Launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="6 + 2C + 3B*? = Chinese (中文) Launch Week" /><published>2017-11-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Long-March-6-2C-3B-Launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Long-March-6-2C-3B-Launch.html">&lt;p&gt;Two or three Chinese rockets are supposeds to launch in week 47/2017 and astronomers are talking about nothing but cigars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lukas*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As expected Long March 3B did not yet launch but will hopefully in the upcoming weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long March 6 and 2C launched successfully and brought their payloads into the correct orbits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week was all about China and our sun smokes cigars? More on that on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here welcome to kNews for week 47/2017 and as always a big shoutout to my kNews Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two or maybe three rockets launch this week in China and the first was a Long March 6 (長征) on Tuesday from Taiyuan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onboard were three Jilin satellites which are floating HD cameras for earth observation. They have a mid range ground resolution of 1.3 meters and will be placed in a polar orbit as most if not all of these gathering environmental data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their carrier is a new Long March 6 which is capable to bring round about a metric ton to such an orbit, which means each of them weighs roughly 300 kilograms. The rocket has three stages from which only the upper one burns a hypergolic fuel. The bottom two ones use Kerosene or Rocket-Propellant-1 like a Falcon 9 or russian Soyuz for example. These are not exactly environmentally friendly but non toxic which means the spent stages which drop to ground are no hazard to the environment. Big thumbs up for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long March 6 will head up and north right after liftoff towards the north pole. The gradual turn is accompanied by the rockets staging process as the lower boosters burn out, until only the upper one is left. This one will likely perform a multitude of burns to bring its payload into the desired orbit. The last steps include payload separation and probably also a short get-out-of-the-way maneuver by the upper stage to make sure it will never collide with its payload as it is being checked and put into service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up was a Long March 2C on Friday from Xichang (西昌).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to were three YaoGan (遥感) satellites. These observe earth aswell but mostly for reconnaissance aka. spy purposes and not environmental monitoring like the previous three. This means they are top secret so there are no images I could share with you and my 3D model is also just made up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rocket has two configurations and I don’t know which one was used to be honest. The most capable one has a solid booster as a third stage and two below which burn hypergolics. The amount of different rockets China has almost make it seem like they develop a new one for each flight. it’s crazy. Everytime I think “oh I got this one modeled already I stand corrected”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, similar to Long March 6 it will head north to achieve a similar orbit. It will probably be a little closer since spy satellites usually want to maximize their resolution which on the other hand leads to a shorter life span. Closer to ground they will experience more orbital decay and consume more fuel to keep them in orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chinese rocket to launch that week is a Long March 3B on sunday from Xichang as well. However, I’m not entirely sure if that will really happen since the source is not really known for being accurate. At least from my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top would be the second pair of Beidou navigation satellites which I covered briefly not to long ago. Similar to the US GPS, Europe’s GALILEO or Russia’s GLONASS, these orbit earth in a medium orbit at round about 20,000 kilometers and an inclination of 56 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long March 3B is one of China’s bigger rockets capable to bring almost 12 metric tons to a low and 5-6 metric tons to such a medium earth orbit. It’s an older one so it uses mostly hypergolics on its four stages including the strap on boosters but has surprisingly a liquid Hydrogen and Oxygen third stage. That’s the most efficient kind of combusting fuel because of the extremely light exhaust particles which reach higher speeds than anything else. However, engine efficiency is only one part of the equation and whether it is worth or not to use it highly depends on the dry mass of the rocket. Hydrogen needs bigger tanks which are more heavy so a hydrogen rocket can not automatically bring more payload to orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the previous two Long March 3B will not head over the poles but instead head south east when I interprete the last webcast correctly. It’s a little hard to follow due to all the kanji symbols so I can’t really read the map very well. However, the number next to degrees north was decreasing so I assume it flew south. Like the other rockets it will go through its launch procedure as it burns out its stages hopefully reaching its desired orbital injection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I want to talk about is our sun’s addiction. I’m just kidding, as you have maybe heard a cigar shaped asteroid from interstellar space called ‘Oumuamua (which is Hawaiian for scout) flew by our sun. Astronomers from all around the world were observing it during its 2 week highly visible passage. It caused excitement among scientists because it’s the first visitor which does probably not belong to our own solar system that we ever witnessed to fly by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how do they know that? Well, its orbit is hyperbolic and not elliptic like the usual comet from the outer solar system would have, which means that it will leave our solar system forever. There is a small chance that it got a gravity assist by an unknown planet though, which could orbit our sun 100 times more distant that earth does. So scientists don’t rule out that it could have been part of the early solar system and didn’t form around another star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, it’s weird cigar like shape is derived from its changing brightness. A change in brightness usually results from an asteroid’s rotation and unless it is perfectly spherical, it reflects more or less of our sun’s light depending on which side is pointing at us. Pretty straight forward but in theory it could instead just have different reflective properties on its surface. So instead of having a cigar like shape it could also have one dark and one bright side. This could have different reasons like a collision could have caused the asteroid to break apart and expose its more dense and shiny inner material. However, that’s just my  speculation and as far as I know astronomers prefer the cigar theory. Probably smokers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real reason is of course more complex since light changes its properties as it get reflected and we also see the comet from different perspectives as it flies by us. So I guess the shape is very certain but its origin not so much. What would you prefer? It being a visitor from interstellar space or flung into the inner solar system by a giant unknown planet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and Thank You for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="china" /><category term="long-march" /><category term="2c" /><category term="3b" /><category term="6" /><category term="47-2017" /><category term="2017" /><summary type="html">Two or three Chinese rockets are supposeds to launch in week 47/2017 and astronomers are talking about nothing but cigars.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_472017.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Delta II, Falcon 9, Long March 4C and Soyuz launch!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Delta-II-Falcon-9-Launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Delta II, Falcon 9, Long March 4C and Soyuz launch!" /><published>2017-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Delta-II-Falcon-9-Launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Delta-II-Falcon-9-Launch.html">&lt;p&gt;In my (almost) weekly kNews episode for week 46/2017 I cover Delta II, Falcon 9, Launch March 4C and a Soyuz rocket launch! Yep, four rockets are planned to launch in a single week which is quite a lot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It seems like the Zuma mission was taken down for a longer period of time. The next launch is a Dragon capsule which does not need the fairing and can therefore launch without issues. The question is now whether Zuma will launch from the launch pad 39A or is moved to launch complex (LC) 40 which is back online after the AMOS (aka. “Facebook Satellite”) pad explosion in 2016. Pad 39A is now being worked on to upgrade it for the upcoming Falcon Heavy launches later this or early next year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Falcon 9 launch was delayed due to a fairing issue on another rocket. The Zuma mission will stand down until SpaceX know what’s going on just to be safe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I confused two Soyuz launches with each other. The one supposed to launch on Nov. 18th launches a “Kosmos” satellite while the “Meteor” satellite is currently due to launch on Nov. 28th. Sorry about that!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;replays&quot;&gt;Replays&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WZITzp2on9w&quot;&gt;Delta II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KkO1kDwvYq0&quot;&gt;Long March 4C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here, welcome to kNews for week 46 and as always a big shoutout to my kNews Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry about no episode for last week but I had some tonsil issues which are finally gone. I’m a cyclist and I showed no respect to the elements and got my well deserved punishment. Anyways, there were no punishments for Arianespace’s Vega and Orbital ATK’s Antares rockets. Both launched successfully last week bringing a communication satellite called Mohammed 6A to orbit for Morocco and a Cygnus spacecraft went to the ISS, which also docked to it Tuesday morning successfully. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First to launch this week was the United Launch Alliance’s Delta II rocket on Wednesday but it was shifted to Saturday at 9:47 UTC from Vandenberg at the US west coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top is JPSS-1, part of the Joint Polar Satellite System which monitors earth for weather forecasting purposes. It will join and replace Suomi NPP which’s 5 year long lifespan is coming to an end this year. But who knows how long it will actually operate. Just btw., Delta II will also carry 5 cubesats as a secondary payload on this mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the 39 meter relatively short and two staged rocket. Its upper stage engine features a large engine bell for maximum efficiency and will give its payload the final push burning hypergolic fuel. The first stage adds most to the rocket’s height and dwarfs the upper one quite a bit. Its core burns Kerosene while the 9, yes 9 strap on boosters are filled with solid propellant. This will be quite the show I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching from Vandenberg the rocket will head south to shot its payload into a polar orbit. Such an orbit is very typical for earth monitoring satellites because as the earth rotates below, it can cover almost the entire surface area. A satellite on a lower inclination like the ISS for example does never fly over the poles which leads to data inconsistencies. You just can’t make super accurate predictions if your data misses such big chunks. That’s why they can’t just strap on every instrument on the ISS and instead have to launch dedicated satellites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is a Chinese Long March 4C which launched earlier than expected on Tuesday from the Taiyuan Satellite Launch Center in northern China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top are two satellites, Fengyun 3D which is similarly to JPSS a weather satellite and Head-1, which will monitor the oceans and rivers for vessels like ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long March 4C has three stages all burning hypergolic fuels which I still find quite nasty. Burning these fuels gets rid of the toxicity but those not entirely empty stages still drop back to ground and the unburned remains get into the environment. Thankfully China renounces hypergolics on its latest of rockets so I hope the older ones will get replaced at some point in a not so distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Delta II, Long March 4C will head for a polar orbit, go through its staging as the lower fuel tanks burn out and hopefully inject the payloads into their desired orbits. The last one launching in 2016 ran into an undisclosed error dooming its payload but that was the only failure so far with 19 preceding successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number 3 to launch this week is a SpaceX Falcon 9 on Thursday or Friday depending on where you live from Cape Canaveral, what a busy week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top is Zuma, a secret satellite which was built in the US but it’s unknown what it does or who paid for it. However, Zuma is probably not as some people say Jacob Zuma, the south african politician. According to some rumours the name might also be just made up to lure people on the wrong track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, below are Falcon’s upper and first booster stage. It will be equipped with its landing gear so we will see another landing. This time it will be at landing zone 1 again so people living in Florida will be able to witness it live from the distance. I’d still recommend to follow their livestream in parallel which is very well made and of course linked in the info box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea in which direction the rocket will fly or what orbit it aims for but I’m pretty sure it will head out over the ocean since everything else would be forbidden launching from Cape Canaveral. Now what do you think about SpaceX launching top secret satellites like this? The satellite maker Northrop Grumman is known for military equipment and could in theory launch a laser weapon to space. Now this is of course made up but is a possible future scenario. Does it matter to you what that payload is and is there stuff you’d not want SpaceX to launch? I’m really curious about your opinion on this since nobody can force them as a private company to just launch everything. But of course, refusing to launch a satellite due to ethnic reasons could have a huge impact on their future missions. That’s a very tough situation to be in I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, after the booster has separated from the upper stage it will turn around and do a boost back burn reversing its trajectory back to where it came from. It will then do its spectacular reentry burn which can be captured in high detail from the ground when landing on land. I really like how they first ignite one, then three engines and how to exhaust plume changes its shape during that event. 
I know there are some sceptics out there who believe these booster landings are all CGI like mine. However, if you really think like that simply go visit Florida and watch it in person. There is also a ton of amateur footage of the landing.
Once the landing is done the livestream will probably again end sooner than usual due to the payload secret nature. So we won’t see it separating but SpaceX will as usual confirm a successful mission on their Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last rocket scheduled for this week is a russian Soyuz launching on Saturday from the new Vostochny cosmodrome in Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On board is yet again another weather satellite for the russian Kosmos program called Meteor M2-1. Exact details are unknown as well so I can’t tell you much about it sadly.
Soyuz will interestingly launch without its famous 4 liquid fueled boosters on the sides and instead just use the core stage. That one is also different using a single fixed NK-33 engine on the bottom which uses four small engines as vernier thrusters to steer the rocket on the way up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the other two weather satellites Meteor will be placed in a circular polar orbit at an altitude of round about 800 to 900 km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in the end some other information regarding my channel. I used to upload and host my craft files on a paid server and also tried to keep my little website updated. However, I just don’t enjoy maintaining all of this so I decided to scrub it and get rid of the cost. Sorry for those who use it! It’s not yet down so if you want a particular craft file linked there go get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and thank you for reading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2017" /><category term="Delta-II" /><category term="Falcon-9" /><category term="Long-March-4C" /><category term="46-2017" /><summary type="html">In my (almost) weekly kNews episode for week 46/2017 I cover Delta II, Falcon 9, Launch March 4C and a Soyuz rocket launch! Yep, four rockets are planned to launch in a single week which is quite a lot!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_462017.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">kNews Space Has a New Home!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/Welcome-to-kNews-Space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="kNews Space Has a New Home!" /><published>2017-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/Welcome-to-kNews-Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/Welcome-to-kNews-Space.html">&lt;p&gt;I decided to cancel my webspace subscription because I basically just link to my content found on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/kNewsSpace&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; channel and do not host my own videos. It would be cool to have my videos hosted on my own server but webspace fast enough to deliver a good experience would be too expensive for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same breath I will also change the appearance of my website to be a little more optimized towards modern devices. I coded everything myself in the past but I am a terrible web developer so I went for a simplisitc &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllthemes.org/themes/lagrange/&quot;&gt;Jerkyll Theme&lt;/a&gt; called Lagrange by “Paul Le”. I like it a lot and will of course personalize it over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I used to host my craft files I use in KSP to showcase the rocket launches. I will try to re-host them here but I’m not sure yet to which extent this is possible on Github Pages. Anyways, I hope you like it and see you on my channel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2017" /><summary type="html">I decided to cancel my webspace subscription because I basically just link to my content found on my YouTube channel and do not host my own videos. It would be cool to have my videos hosted on my own server but webspace fast enough to deliver a good experience would be too expensive for me.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22001_welcome.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry></feed>