<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.knews.space/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.knews.space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-05-19T12:29:07+02:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/</id><title type="html">kNews Space</title><subtitle>Rocket Launch and Space News</subtitle><author><name>Lukas</name></author><entry><title type="html">Japan’s Smallest Launcher &amp;amp; Swimming Boosters</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Japan-Worls-Smallest-Rocket-SS520.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan's Smallest Launcher &amp; Swimming Boosters" /><published>2018-02-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Japan-Worls-Smallest-Rocket-SS520</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Japan-Worls-Smallest-Rocket-SS520.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 05/2018 (Jan. 29 - Feb. 4)  I cover Japan’s smallest launch vehicle, Falcon 9, Long March 2D and Soyuz launch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Japan finally launches the world’s smallest orbital rocket and SpaceX booster swims. This and more, now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey guys, Lukas here welcome to kNews for week 05/2018 and as always a big shout out to my kNews Boosters who support me creating these videos on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I know it is not the most recent news as this comes out but I really want to feature every single week this year so I’m still catching up on my backlog. I hope you don’t mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up was a SpaceX Falcon 9 that launched from Cape Canaveral. It went east following a 26 degrees inclined Geosynchronous Transfer Orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that usually means there was a communication satellite on board and indeed it was GovSat-1 built by Orbital ATK for Luxembourg. Once in its final orbit it will hover at 21.5 degrees east over Africa and will be able to each Europe, the Atlantic ocean, Africa, the Indian ocean and parts of Asia with its steerable dish antennas.  It has many purposes ranging from civilian to military applications. An example would be emergency satellite calls from ships in distress out in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise Falcon 9 launched with landing legs and grid fins attached although it would not attempt to land on its drone ship nor at the landing zone. The result was actually pretty funny but more on that in just a sec. Up top the booster was as always the upper stage carrying the payload protected by the two fairings which SpaceX is still trying to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch proceeded as expected, Falcon went up and then received a kick to the side to perform a turn towards its desired inclination. Roughly 2 minutes and 30 seconds into the flight the booster’s tanks are almost empty and it gets staged away to set the upper stage free which goes on with the main mission. The fairings separate shortly after and at least one of them is used to test SpaceX new recovery system. It basically re enters back into the atmosphere stabilized by cold gas thrusters which simply release pressurize gas in little puffs. Once below a certain speed the parachute gets released which is still a big problem for SpaceX. According to Elon Musk himself the main issue is the fairing size. It causes so much turbulences in the air that it is hard to operate a parachute above it. The goal is then to catch it with Mr. Stevens, a ship that is waiting in the ocean. It looks like parachuting things down in a controlled fashion is not as easy as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the booster also reentered back into the atmosphere and while there is no droneship waiting for it to come home, it still performed a landing burn. This one is however special since SpaceX wants to get more efficient at it so they now fire three engines continuously for landing. They previously fired three too but two shut down just before touchdown. It worked out well, much better than SpaceX actually thought. The booster sunk into the water and tipped over gently staying intact. Yep, it did not explode as it used to do. This is because it is highly pressurized to its limits and falling over means the pressure exceeds what the booster is designed to. So my personal speculation is, the booster sunk vertically into the water to then bounce back sideways or it had a really lucky wave that damped its impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk joked about pulling it all the way back to the coast but the sad truth is it was destroyed. The booster malfunctioned and did not release its pressure correctly and was therefore a hazard. Not knowing what was going to happen B1032 was attacked and destroyed I assume as part of a spontaneous training maneuver. However, the details are unclear and I’m not quite sure why they didn’t simply send the termination signal. The booster is packed with explosives just in case something goes wrong at lift off but I don’t know how much control SpaceX has about that when it’s landing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, back at the upper stage it has accelerated the payload up to the correct speed to release GovSat-1 which will go on with its mission to circularize its orbit on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up now in quick succession were a Soyuz for Russia which launched off of their new Vostochny launch site on February 1st. It’s destination was a low earth sun synchronous orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Long March 2D for China which launched from their northern launch site in Jiuquan. That already indicates a similar destination which was also a sun synchronous orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top Soyuz were 5 satellites, the two main Russian of type Kanopus-V and several nanosatellites. Most notably at least for me are four of type S-Net from Germany. These are the best satellites! Totally un-biased! But wait a second… S-Net: What does that remind me of… I forgot. Wasn’t too important I guess. These satellites are supposed to test a nanosat swarm. Instead of having a few rather complicated larger ones that can maneuver themselves around to sit in specific spots, this swarm would just float around randomly in an orbital plane to form a dense network sort of like a brain. Instead of talking to one satellite of the constellation you would essentially talk to the constellation as a whole just pointing your dish upwards into the sky. Terrific! We could for example use it to control autonomous drones and such since they hadn’t to bother pointing their antenna in the right direction, just up. The simplicity of each satellite would also make it much easier to produce them with a high degree of automation without many humans involved thus cheaper. That sounds like a really good idea if you ask me. But enough trolling, S-Net will not take over the world just yet since this is only a test and it is of course not designed to do that. Involved into the mission were also many students of the Tech-University in Berlin, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching on top Long March 2D is the main scientific payload CSES or China Seismo-Electromagnetic Satellite, and several nanosatellites. CSES is a collaboration between China and Italia which will gather data about earth’s proximity most notably the iono- and magnetosphere which interact with the sun’s radiation.This research will help to better understand how events like solar flares or the solar wind in general impact our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last rocket launch for that week happened on February 3rd in Uchinoura, Japan. The world’s smallest orbital launch vehicle SS-520 took off into an elliptic low to medium earth orbit inclined by 31 degrees as part of a demonstration mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top was a small nanosatellite called TRICOM-1R with a mass around 3 kg. It’s just a test and is not equipped with many instruments but cameras to take some nice pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher is a sounding rocket where sounding comes from sonde or probe. It typically shoots a 100 to 150 kg kg payload on a suborbital trajectory to take measurements and perform experiments. However, instead of a heavier payload it carried a third stage which can boost tiny payloads up to orbital speeds. It’s less than 10 meter tall and has a mass of 2.6 metric tons. That’s like a beetle pulling a small trailer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to get such a small rocket into orbit is thrust, a lot of it. Especially on the first two stages. Every second thrusting upwards counts because earth’s gravity pulls at it. The less time it takes the rocket to release all of its energy the less time it spends fighting gravity and losing speed. That’s quite difficult to achieve in KSP and my launcher weighs three times as much as SS520. That’s because KSPs parts are made out of lead or something to compensate for the smaller planet. It would be just too easy to get to orbit otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the spin stabilized rocket reaches space and orbit really fast where it releases its payload. While the first and second stage drop in the ocean the third will stay in space like the payload but the orbit will decay over time as it dips quite deep into the atmospheric remains at 150 kms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="japan" /><category term="smallest" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="world" /><category term="record" /><category term="ss520" /><category term="govsat1" /><category term="05-2018" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 05/2018 (Jan. 29 - Feb. 4) I cover Japan’s smallest launch vehicle, Falcon 9, Long March 2D and Soyuz launch!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_052018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX Falcon Heavy Test Flight… Finally!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Falcon-Heavy-Test-Flight.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX Falcon Heavy Test Flight... Finally!" /><published>2018-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Falcon-Heavy-Test-Flight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Falcon-Heavy-Test-Flight.html">&lt;p&gt;SpaceX Falcon Heavy finally launches for the first time! On board is a cherry red Tesla Roadster and I discuss the launch in a kNews Special!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(2018/02/07):
  Wow! Falcon Heavy launched its payload successfully to orbit and what a sight that was! The side boosters separated flawlessly and so did the core stage. However, only the side boosters managed to land safely while the center core failed to ignite 2 of 3 engines at landing and crashed into the ocean at almost terminal velocity. The speed max. something reaches within the atmosphere where its weight and the drag balance each other out. The center core did not smash directly into the drone ship but still managed to damage two of its engines as it came in from the side. It remains unknown whether the drone ship can be fixed for the next launch or not.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the upper stage achieved another very important goal. It reignited 6 hours into the flight shooting the Tesla Roadster not only to Mars but beyond. But don’t expect any nice imagery because the batteries will be long flat before it even leaves our planet’s sphere of influence. Elon Musk stated that they may hold for a total of 12 hours. Sending HD data across space is quite demanding when it comes to enery consumption and the vehicle has no solar panels! It will now coast silently for a few months and ultimately reach the asteroid belt and Cere’s orbit before it does a deep dive back into the inner solar system again flying by earth’s orbit once again. However, it should not approach earth closely for many years to come but the final word is not yet spoken since the final trajectory was not expected and has to be simulated by SpaceX and or astronomers!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Congratulations to SpaceX for proving their design and hopefully waking up all their competitors who now have to seriously think about canceling/changing everything non-reusable and focus on more future proof rockets. As Elon Musk said during a press conference, a reusable Falcon Heavy will be barely more expensive than a Falcon 9 initially costing about 90 million dollars. Their heavy lift rocket itself will not out compete anyone just yet but the cost savings from reusing the boosters will allow SpaceX to fund their next and most important project - the BFR. This monster will be fully reusable and it will take an estimated amount of 4 years to develop it and perform its first maiden flight in the full stack consisting of the booster and the big interplanetry ship. 4 years is not a lot of time and considering that SpaceX has all the necessary software and data to land rockets wherever they want, it is not as unrealistic as it seems. The development speed will likely exceed the one of Falcon also taking into account a steadily growing company. Not only in size but also in knowledge. They just learn a whole lot of new stuff others don’t by reusing hardware and pushing the limits further out. Luckily others can learn from SpaceX’ faults and achievements to catch up quickly - if they want. The will to make it happen is very important and I believe public interest plays a big role in it. The more people ask tough questions regarding this issue the more they will have to think about solutions and in the end good answers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delayed by many years and now finally here. Falco…. no, not that one Solo, SpaceX Falcon Heavy! Now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here, welcome to this kNews Special and as always a big shout out to my kNews Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I’m the only one but it’s really hard to believe that the day has finally come and we will see this particular bird of prey fly for the first time. It will take off of the only operational launch site that supports it in Cape Canaveral. So yes, if it explodes on the launch pad that means SpaceX won’t attempt it anytime soon again. So whatever you wish for, make sure not exploding over the pad is on the very top of the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk himself said in an interview that he considers it a win even if they can only avoid just that. But why? Falcon Heavy is hyped up a lot and at least SpaceX tries to keep the expectations low. This is a test flight and there are many things that could go wrong because they are simply unknown. But that’s good because test flights exist to uncover flaws so they don’t happen on crewed missions in the future. So I’m pretty sure they will not be very gentle with Falcon Heavy on a test flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX as a private company somehow relies on the public trust and especially people who are not very familiar with spaceflight could treat an explosion during such a test as severe as during a Falcon 9 launch. It is of course not. A Falcon 9 explosion during flight would far more severe at this point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of it, the launch date is February 6th 2018 at 18:30 UTC from Cape Canaveral. There is a three hour long launch window so in case you are planning to watch it live, make sure to bring plenty of time and some snacks! The backup day is the day after should they run into trouble but so far at least the weather looks go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On board will be… well a cherry red Tesla Roadster, what else. One of the first cars Tesla produced. Now it of course looks silly to launch a car to space and maybe it really is, but test flights generally involve undisclosed dummy payloads which could’ve been even more silly in the past without anyone knowing it. Unlike government agencies who don’t really rely on marketing, SpaceX or Tesla for that matter does so it is not a bad idea to launch something that would hit all the front pages showing it off. But I think the most important reason for SpaceX is to simply reach more people and get them interested into space. Tesla’s destination is a Mars orbit which should not be confused with an orbit around Mars. The Mars orbit is the trajectory the planet follows around the sun so the Roadster will become a neighbor of Mars. It is yet unknown how close the Tesla will get but I personally don’t expect any imagery with a big Mars in the background unless they have a telescope on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Falcon Heavy like its smaller brother Falcon 9 uses two core stages and as an addition two more first stages boosters as strap ons. If you are familiar with rocketry this will immediately remind you of the United launch Alliance’s Delta IV Heavy and they are indeed very similar when it comes to size. However, Delta IV uses cryogenic Hydrogen as fuel which is far less dense than Falcon’s Kerosene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a comparison liquid Hydrogen has a density of round about 70 kg/m³. That’s 14 times lower than water which weighs 1000 kg per cubic meter. These cubes here have the same mass essentially. Now, Kerosene is very similar to water when it comes to the mass per volume so you can imagine that a Hydrogen rocket is much bigger for its weight than a Kerosene one. The thing missing there is the liquid oxygen which mixes it all up again but that’s only a ballpark and not the exact relation between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just important to understand why a Delta IV Heavy weighs in at 730,000 kg while Falcon Heavy although a bit more compact, has a mass of 1.42 million kg. That’s almost twice as Heavy as the currently biggest rocket out there and it therefore also needs twice the thrust to get off the ground and that means more noise and more boom should something go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first dangerous part of the launch is the take off itself. Each of the rocket’s 27 Merlin engines pushes its exhaust out of the nozzle at speeds above the speed of sound. This means the exhaust gas generates a lot of strong pressure waves in the air which hit the ground and sadly also bounce back towards the vehicle. Now I’m sure SpaceX has done a lot of simulations but you can never be 100% sure. These off the ground bouncing sonic booms could make the long rocket body oscillate and oscillation means energy can build up. This energy could than make the rocket tanks experience more pressure they are designed to and fail so the rocket has to get away off the pad as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Falcon Heavy has successfully survived that part the next event to keep an eye on is the rotation it does. I’m not sure if and how they will rotate the rocket on its maiden flight but even KSP models that one pretty well. The side boosters have a lot of mass and rotating them around causes a lot of shearing forces at the coupling between all three bodies. This could again induce some kind of oscillation from wobbling around destroying the coupling and ultimately the vehicle. This is unknown territory for SpaceX and it all depends on how well their simulation tools predict the real behavior. I could imagine they also did real life tests by twisting and bending these in all possible directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is of course not the last challenge because soon after Falcon Heavy will go through its maximum aerodynamic pressure on the vehicle. This is where its speed combined with the ambient air pressure generate the highest forces on the rocket body now pulling hard on the both side mounted boosters. This and the airflow around the rocket could again lead to some strange unknown oscillations which would of course again lead to an explosion mid air. However, at this point in flight at least the launch pad is safe so I’m pretty sure you will hear a lot of cheers in the stream already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last risky event is the strap-on booster separation. While I’m sure SpaceX has tested their mechanism on ground, having endured all these stresses during launch who knows if they will still work properly. Even separating off sync could lead to unknown destructive behavior but the worst part would be off course if one or both wouldn’t separate correctly. If something gets stuck while the booster tries to get lose Goodbye Falcon Heavy and Goodbye Cherry Red Tesla. That is really a lot that can go wrong in the first couple of minutes but if both boosters separate successfully and Falcon Heavy stays in one piece, this test launch was a full success already no matter what happens after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest is pretty much standard Falcon 9 procedure. Be it the booster landings that follow or the upper stage release and burn towards Mars. Speaking of it, while the side boosters rotate and burn back towards the landing zone at land the core will go on pushing forward. As the core stage drains almost out of fuel it will also separate and attempt landing on a drone ship far out in the middle of the Atlantic ocean. The upper stage will meanwhile continue to speed up its payload until it reaches escape velocity. The speed needed to leave earth and put the vehicle into an orbit around the sun maybe intersecting Mars orbit at some point. However, the reason I think the Tesla won’t flyby Mars directly is the launch window towards Mars opens in a few months from now around May and it’s just too soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, in order to get to Mars somewhat efficiently you have to launch just before earth overtakes Mars on its orbit around the sun. This happens roughly every two years so it is pretty much coincidence that we are that close right now. If SpaceX wanted to flyby Mars they would probably wait a couple more months but I don’t know how fast the upper stage can speed up the payload. The Tesla seems incredibly light compared to regular satellites so there is a very very small chance that SpaceX could take a less efficient route. Instead of such a transfer which exactly intersects the Martian orbit at its Apoapsis, the highest point of its orbit, they could accelerate faster and push the trajectory closer towards the sun. This would mean the Roadster would take a quicker route reaching Mars orbit sooner. It would then of course be able to take a close up picture of the red planet but it would still not be able to stay there. It would simply fly by and get flung away into space orbiting the sun for millions of years without meeting Mars again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally doubt they would do that even if they could because flying by planets usually means you have to be able to do correction burns along the way to make really sure not to hit Mars by accident. A small deviation in the beginning has a huge impact on the overall trajectory. That would be way too complicated for such a test flight since then you also had to make sure everything is protected against micrometeorites, the sun’s radiation, solar flares and so on. So I don’t expect anything more but also not less than a few really cool pictures and maybe video of a Tesla Roadster drifting away from our pale blue dot. Good luck SpaceX and I really hope you guys are all able to watch it live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this Special episode an I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="special" /><category term="spacex" /><category term="falcon" /><category term="heavy" /><category term="first" /><category term="maiden" /><category term="test" /><category term="flight" /><category term="tesla" /><category term="roadster" /><category term="05-2018" /><summary type="html">SpaceX Falcon Heavy finally launches for the first time! On board is a cherry red Tesla Roadster and I discuss the launch in a kNews Special!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_s052018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Arianespace’s Ariane 5 Dodged Termination!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Ariane-5-Dodged-Termination.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arianespace's Ariane 5 Dodged Termination!" /><published>2018-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Ariane-5-Dodged-Termination</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Ariane-5-Dodged-Termination.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 04/2018 I talk about Ariane 5’s close call to termination and a Chinese Long March 2C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arianespace closed its eyes and prayed as Ariane 5 flew off course. This and more, now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here, welcome to kNews for week 04/2018 and as always a big shout out to my kNews Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next to Ariane 5 there was another Chinese launch. Long March 2C took off from Xichang on Thursday towards a by 35 degrees inclined low earth orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top was the fourth set of three satellites for their reconnaissance constellation called Yaogan and a small secondary payload called NanoSat-1A. Yaogan translates to remote sensing and consists of several satellites flying one after another in different orbital planes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rocket is one of China’s smaller ones able to lift 4 metric tons to low earth orbit. That of course varies depending on the inclination but that is roughly where Yaogan’s went. Its setup is a little unusual from other launch vehicles. The optional upper stage burns solid propellant while the two stages below burn liquid Hypergolics. However, since it is optional I assume it was not used in this particular launch since it was not mentioned anywhere or at least not where I looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after take off the rocket turned east flying over land due to the launch sites location. I saw some video footage of it recorded by citizens and that is just drazy. Even on smartphones without a zoom these appear incredibly close. I expect more and more of such footage to pop up online as rocket launches get more popular in China. They plan to launch 40 rockets this year alone which is on average almost one per week and they will also try to get another rover to the moon which I will of course cover as well. Now why are 40 rockets a big deal? Well, even if funding plays not a big role building and launching rockets for China, the launch cadence would highly benefit from reusable boosters and as they are switching to non-hypergolic and more efficient propellants, I’m sure they will come up with an at least partly reusable Long March at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the rocket went through its staging and burned out it released the satellitew which from then on placed themselves into the required locations autonomously. This is simply done by changing the orbital altitude slightly. Moving lower makes the satellite orbit faster and moving higher makes it orbit more slowly. The satellites orient themselves using cameras pointing at the stars. In space without a bright sky to look through one can see the stars 24/7 as long as the camera lens is not pointed towards the earth, the moon or the sun. These objects are incredibly bright and would flood the image sensor with too much light to also capture stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now to Ariane 5. Ariane Ariane Ariane. What shall I say. I’m kind of disappointed to be honest. The rocket itself is off course innocent and just did what it was programmed to. It launched on Thursday as usual from French Guiana in South America and the targeted orbit was a Geosynchronous Transfer one inclined by 3 degrees. The launch site is almost at the equator which means it can pretty much fly into any inclination as long as it avoids flying over land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main payload consisted of SES-14 which will be positioned at 47.5 degrees west and Al-Yah-3 moving to 20 degrees west. Both are communication satellites sitting stationary at their geosynchronous slots 35,000 kilometers away. Strapped to SES-14 is a payload for NASA called GOLD. The Global-scale Observations of the Limb and Disk. It’s actually pretty cool to strap some scientific equipment to commercial satellites and I hope this will be much more common in the future. GOLD will observe the full disk of our planet at once and its limb This is the circular edge around it which it will observe in the ultraviolet spectrum to gather more data about the weather in the upper atmo- thermo and ionospheres. The outermost layers which until now weren’t given as much attention as the rest of earth’s gas cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ariane 5 stands as usual 55 m tall powered by its efficient cryogenic upper and first stages burning liquid Hydrogen and Oxygen. However, strapped to the sides are giant solid rocket boosters similar to the Space Shuttle which are on the opposite side of the efficiency spectrum. The total efficiency all things combined is still relatively high because the majority of speed is added by the efficient cores. The boosters basically just buy some time in space generating the majority of vertical speed that gets things to space while the cores add the precious horizontal velocity that keeps them in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the beginning Ariane 5 has had an anomaly which was to my surprise completely ignored in the live webcast. Now, I sadly missed the launch itself by a couple minutes so I was not able to follow it live from the beginning. Reviewing the video footage afterwards, knowing something went wrong, was incredibly strange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, what I’ve learned is the main animation Arianespace shows is just that. An animation not a simulation of the incoming telemetry of the rocket. It does always the same and does not reflect what is actually happening. The animation went through all the stages of flight although they had lost telemetry very early into the mission. I understand that at least redaring the general public. However, on stream you could also see the customers which saw the same images and were completely unaware of the situation smiling into the cameras as the speakers told all was going nominally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is only my interpretation of what I saw and there is a chance I could be wrong. The official investigation is still ongoing and I will of course share their conclusions as they will be published. Until then let’s have a discussion on what you think about all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pay really close attention to the livestream, you can see two screens showing real data. On is the trajectory on the map and the other shows the altitude. Here is a crop showing in green, the trajectory Ariane should have followed and in yellow the one it really went. This is quite some deviation I woudl say. Instead of following a low inclined 3-6 degrees trajectory, Ariane 5 went further south at roughly 21 degrees where the payload ended up being released. This is a huge difference and judging by the close proximity to the coast, it could’ve been terminated. The boosters separate early into the flight and normally crash into the ocean approximately 500 kms away from the coast in their drop zone. Not so at this particular launch. It’s hard to tell where they crashed but it must’ve been very very close. I don’t know how big their drop zone is no ship is allowed to enter during launch but this could’ve been well outside of it. However, that’s speculation and I hope they will release such information when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having another look at the telemetry you can see the yellow line jumped back onto the green one on both images. That looks weird but can be explained by the switch in tracking stations. The one at the launch site in Galliot uses three dishes which means it can easily track down the exact position of the vehicle basically having all three coordinates in 3D space. The second in Natal however, has only one dish, at least as shown on ESA’s website. They are pretty old from 2002 so it could have changed. Having only one dish available would make it much harder to track the exact position so what I think it did is to simply track one coordinate along the calculated line the rocket should follow. That would explain the jump in the telemetry data. Soon after the signal was lost which makes sense since the rocket went completely out of sight far at the bottom. Interesting to note is the trajectory was slightly lower which also makes sense since moving into a higher inclination, the rocket can make less use of the earth’s equatorial speed to reach orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for Arianespace the rocket still made it to space sucessfully and while it is in a different inclination, the satellites will be able to correct the course. But that will of course cost fuel and therefore decrease the satellites life span. It’s therefore at least a partial failure so the insurance companies are probably already discussing the lost value and such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that remains and has to be answered is how much risk did Arianespace take into account not terminating the flight as it went of course - if it really did. Did they put people in danger or where there no ships around to get hit by the boosters? And am I overly harsh with Arianespace or is this really much more serious than it looks. Tell me what you think about it because I honestly don’t know if I judge this correctly or not. The livestream was just incredibly strange. I can’t link it because Arianespace removed it and I have no idea how legal those reuploads are, but who seeks shall find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that concludes this episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like - and yes, Falcon Heavy, I know, soon. Have a nice one guys. Auf Wiedersehen and thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="ariane-5" /><category term="arianespace" /><category term="anomaly" /><category term="failure" /><category term="partial" /><category term="termination" /><category term="ses" /><category term="04-2018" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 04/2018 I talk about Ariane 5’s close call to termination and a Chinese Long March 2C.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_042018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rocket Lab’s Electron Scares Kiwis and Shoots Discoballs!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-AtlasV-SBIRS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rocket Lab's Electron Scares Kiwis and Shoots Discoballs!" /><published>2018-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-AtlasV-SBIRS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-AtlasV-SBIRS.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 03/2018 I talk about Rocket Lab’s second rocket launch from New Zealand, Epsilon, Long March 11 and Atlas V!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By rocket scared Kiwis Animation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey guys, Lukas here, welcome to kNews for week 03/2018 and as always a big shout out to my Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have to catch up with my schedule so I decided to make one or two lightning fast episodes so I can actually release them ahead of time again. But that doesn’t mean I will speak fast. (Heavy Breathing) But not that fast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week with 5, last week had ONLY 4 launches with the first one being Epsilon for Japan on Wednesday. The rocket launched from Uchinoura (内之浦) and went south aiming for a Sun Synchronous Polar Bear. I mean orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top is ASNARO-2 or Advanced Satellite with New system Architecture for Observation. It has a big RADAR up top with a foldable dish antenna. RADAR stands for Radio Detection and Ranging and is one of the oldest and simplest methods to measure a distance wirelessly. Except maybe guesstimation. It is simple because you don’t actually need a complex circuit. You can build a simple radar with things you have lying around at home but you wouldn’t be able to tell the distance, just the fact that there is something in the way reflecting your signal. ASNARO-2 uses it scan the ground with a resolution of up to 1m. You can think of it like a camera that uses a big flashlight to light up earth to then make a picture of it. This allows you to map the planet independent from day or night. This would be very difficult using regular light because, well, a flashlight bright enough to light up the earth from space would consume way too much energy. The energy of electromagnetic radiation can be calculated using a simple formula: E = hf where H is the Planck constant and F the frequency. Visible light is in the Terahertz range while radio waves are generated with a couple hundred kHz. So it takes in the order of one million to one billion times less energy to make radio waves swing and you can therefore easily light up earth to make a picture. One important side effect is we can not see it so nobody therefore is disturbed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next was a Long March 11 for China. It launched on Friday from Jiuquan (酒泉 Wine-Springs) towards north also into a sun synchronous polar orbit following the terminator in the evening. This is the line which separates the day from the night and not Arnold Schwarzenegger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On board were 6 satellites, the two main ones being from type Jilin-1 for earth observation aka telescopes and the other four are cubesats. The first pair are technology demonstrators which test a variety of systems in space like stabilisation and the other ones are communication satellites from which one is Kepler-2 for the Canadian startup Kepler-Communications based in Toronto. Their plan for the future is to create a Space Internet you can access from anywhere around the world similar to Iridium oder what SpaceX and other are planing. That’s of course quite a task for a small startup but this first launch proves they are heading in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long March 11 is one of Chinas smallest launchers able to bring 350 kg of payload into such a sun synchronous orbit. This was only its third flight since 2015 so there is not yet a very high demand for these. I’m not sure how that will look like in the future but at least many small rocket companies expect the small satellite market to grow. The future will tell I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is Atlas V which launched Friday night from Cape Canaveral. And that is me trying to sound american. Its destination was a Geosynchronous Transfer Orbit or GTO for short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top Atlas was another satellite for the Space Based Infrared System. A satellite that monitors infrared light sources on earth. Now you might ask, why is that. Well, the reason is simply to track big missiles like rockets. Their hot exhaust shines so brightly in the infrared spectrum of light, it can be seen from space despite all the other heat coming off the surface. Even a raging bushfire does not quite reach its brightness so attempts to cover up such missile launches are probably in vain. At least as long as nobody develops a cooler way to launch stuff to space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlas V launched in its weird asymmetric configuration using a single strap on booster on the side. Its main core engine the RD-180 has enough control authority to make sure the rocket keeps heading in the right direction because everyone who play KSP knows, a single booster really wants to make a rocket flip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last launch that happened last week was of course Rocket Lab’s Electron. After many delays since 2017 they were finally able to launch off of New Zealand towards a polar orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next to the three smallsats I already covered in a previous episode Rocket Lab decided to add a fourth undisclosed payload. A Disco Ball named Humanity Star. The idea is … well to make people look in the sky and get inspired by the glittering satellite passing by. I personally have mixed feeling about this. While it’s certainly a nice thought I bet there are a lot of astronomers who are not pleased by that. Pointing your telescope at the night sky there is now one more object they have to avoid that would ruin their long exposure shot. A long exposure is necessary to catch very dim objects. A flying by disco ball would make it look like this. Now luckily humanity star will not orbit forever and its altitude will decay over the course of roughly 9 months. They have also set up a website for everybody to track it in case you want to see it I will link in the description. Now what’s your opinion on humanity star? I would especially like to know what astronomers think about it. I’m not sure how intrusive such things really are considering it can only be seen right after sunset when the sky is dark and the sun is still hitting the disco ball from the side. So maybe it’s in the end not that big of a deal at all. I guess the cheaper launches get the more often we will actually see joke and marketing payloads. Imagine a satellite projecting text and images with a laser onto clouds from orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this quicker than usual episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehn and Thank You for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="rocket-lab" /><category term="electron" /><category term="humanity-star" /><category term="atlasv-sbirs" /><category term="epsilon" /><category term="long-march-11" /><category term="03-2018" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 03/2018 I talk about Rocket Lab’s second rocket launch from New Zealand, Epsilon, Long March 11 and Atlas V!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_032018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Russia Resurrects Secret Project CORONA!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Russia-Ressurects-CORONA-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia Resurrects Secret Project CORONA!" /><published>2018-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Russia-Ressurects-CORONA-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Russia-Ressurects-CORONA-Project.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 02/2018 I talk about Russia’s secret project CORONA, three Long March, a PSLV and the last Delta IV (M) launch ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia resurrected an older program of their Single Stage to Orbit vehicle. That and more, now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, Lukas here, welcome to kNews for week 02/2018 and as always a big shout out to my kNews Boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But CORONA is not the only news in the rocket department. There were also several rocket launches last week which I don’t want to forget. Especially China is at it again with three ones in a row. The first was a Long March 2D on Tuesday from Taiyuan ( 太原市 Very-Original-City), the second a Long March 3B on Thursday from Xichang (西昌市 West-Chang-City) and another 2D on Saturday from Jiuquan (酒泉市 - Wine-Spring-City).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top Long March 3B were two more navigation satellites for their BeiDou-3 Navigation System which will be as usual placed in one of their Medium Earth Orbital Planes at 21,500 km. The rocket was used in its 4-staged variant using an optional upper stage called Yuǎnzhēng (远征) which is literally translated to Far-Journey or Expedition. However, I think Far-Journey makes a little more sense to me considering the upper stage allows the rocket to carry a smaller payload to higher orbits. Please correct me on that if you speak Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other two Long March 2D rockets will carry two pairs of earth observing satellites, two of type SuperView and one of each LKW-3 and Saudisat-5B. These are all relatively small satellites which were brought into a polar orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next launch took place a little further west in India. Their PSLV rocket or Polar Satellite Launch Vehicle launched on Friday from the Satish Dhawan Space Center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top were many different satellites with the main one being from type Cartosat-2. It has a mass of just over 700 kg and will as the name suggests be used to help map the world. Basically an Indian Google Maps when I understand correctly but I’m not sure on that one. The other 30 satellites on board have a combined mass of 600 kg and range from communication to weather monitoring. The most interesting one at least from an outsider’s perspective is one for Japan called CNUSail-1. It is a solar sail demonstrator which will demonstrate how to unfold a 2 sqm large sail in space and then use it as a drag sail to re-enter back into the atmosphere. They will basically simulate the sun’s radiation pressure using drag to gather data on how their sail behaves to make adjustments to their design before a bigger and more expensive one is build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such unfoldable sails could be incredibly useful especially when it comes to in orbit station keeping. Right now satellite have to carry a lot of propellant to stay in the right orbital spot and this will hopefully change with reliable sail system. Right now it’s a little too risky since the sail mechanism could simply break rendering an expensive satellite useless. India’s PSLV launched in its biggest XL configuration using of the stronger variant boosters generating a total of 9000 kNs at launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last rocket launch is the United launch Alliance’s Delta IV which launched on Friday as well from Vandenberg. Up top was a top secret spy satellite for the National Reconnaissance Office called NROL-47. There are some sad news about the launcher because this was the last Delta IV flight in this particular setup using solid strap on boosters. The main reason everybody talks about is Atlas V which is very similar in capability and cheaper. Atlas V launches for roughly 30% less that’s true but I think such a price difference never really was an issue. Delta IV is cleaner, more efficient and uses engines build in the US. I actually believe the ULA would’ve much rather retired Atlas V since they still need Delta IV Heavy and will not stop building the cores anyways. So I personally don’t think it’s Atlas V that killed Delta IV, it’s.. you know who. The competition from private rocket companies really stepped up in the last years and what we are now witnessing is the beginning of a new space era where the biggest limiting factor is no longer the availability but the price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally the most surprising news that came up is Russia’s CORONA. I’ve never actually heard about that before and doing some superficial research it sounds incredibly interesting with some neat twists in the rocket design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re familiar with reusable rocketry this shape will immediately remind you of the old Delta Clipper. It was developed for NASA in the early 1990s and it could launch, maneuver and land back vertically like a Falcon 9 booster a decade ahead of time. There are some cool videos online I highly recommend to watch if you haven’t seen them yet. The project was sadly canceled and I’m not entire sure why but I assume budget cuts will have played a big role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key difference between the Delta Clipper and CORONA is the engine. It’s an aerospike! Since this is a single stage to orbit craft it goes through different regimes on its way to space and as the atmospheric properties change, the engine usually doesn’t. Now in order to follow you have to know a rocket engine works like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rocket fuel mixes and ignites in the engine’s combustion chamber where a high pressure is created. The atmospheric pressure is around the engine and it is much lower. A fundamental property of how fluids and gases behave is that pressures mix and even themselves out. Doing this the engine’s exhaust leaves the nozzle and expands in all directions almost equally. Like a semi sphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shooting out to the back not violating any laws of physics the rocket has to shoot in the opposite direction as a result of that. Yey thrust. To maximize the thrust gains an engine bell is used to direct more of the exhaust backwards and not to the sides. But the exhaust does not expand infinitely within the atmosphere because the exhaust pressure reaches the atmospheric one at some point. This is where the engine bell should end, no more is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the problem is, going to space the atmospheric pressure decreases towards 0 and since the typical engine bell can not grow, the rocket loses thrust efficiency on the way up. Now don’t confuse this with the exhaust speed efficiency from KSP. The total thrust still increases as it goes up but it could increase even more and this is exactly the issue the Aerospike engine fixes. It has a variable engine bell which changes during flight but it’s not a physical one you can touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this you have to know that an engine bell is not the only way to redirect the exhaust backwards. Instead of using a normal nozzle where the pressure expands in all directions, you can also simply shoot the exhaust towards an inverted engine bell. The spike. The effect is the same, the exhaust is redirected downwards producing thrust. Now, the problem is the same. The spike has a fixed size and had to change its length during flight similar to a bell. This is where aerodynamics come into play and where it gets incredibly complicated. However, the basics are simple. The spike is truncated into a stump making it much shorter and lighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as the hot exhaust rushes past this stump the ambient air gets caught filling the gap. A very strong whirl forms and guess what this whirl does. Yep, it creates an aerodynamic spike or aerospike out of gas because it can’t go anywhere. The whirl motion is the important part here that allows energy or momentum to be transferred from behind the engine, to the stump. It creates a push basically. A very neat thing about this aerospike is that it continuously adapts to changes in the air pressure around the engine and always maintains the perfect shape at all stages of flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia’s CORONA is supposed to use such a large aerospike engine which consist of many tiny thrusters firing at the truncated aerospike. However, it is unknown how far into the development this rocket is and I don’t expect it to fly anytime soon. It’s a little speculative but the weird shape of it could be an indication that the whole thing is meant to re-enter and therefore looks like a stretched capsule. The final design could still look different and I will of course keep you updated on future developments. Tell me what you think about the whole concept. Is Russia serious? Will they catch up when it comes to reusability? And now that Delta IV is gone, who do you think will be next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and Thank You for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2018" /><category term="russia" /><category term="corona" /><category term="ssto" /><category term="reusable" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="secret" /><category term="superview" /><category term="lkw-3" /><category term="saudisat-5b" /><category term="nrol-47" /><category term="cartosat-2" /><category term="india" /><category term="02-2018" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 02/2018 I talk about Russia’s secret project CORONA, three Long March, a PSLV and the last Delta IV (M) launch ever.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_022018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What I Look Forward to in Space 2018</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/What-I-Look-Forward-in-Space-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I Look Forward to in Space 2018" /><published>2018-01-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/What-I-Look-Forward-in-Space-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/What-I-Look-Forward-in-Space-2018.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for Week 01/2018 I talk about the recent ZUMA launch of SpaceX and what I look forward to in 2018!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2018/01/10): Rumours about a failed Zuma mission have apeared. From an official statepoint there were no issues with SpaceX’ Falcon 9 rocket at any point of time. The telemetry looks norminal which means the rocket performed as expected. SpaceX can’t say much about the mission due to its secret nature but according to some speculation on the SpaceX Subreddit, the satellite separation mechanism could have failed. To be clear: This particular part on this particular launch was provided by the contractor itself. It was not build by SpaceX. If this is true SpaceX would not be the only one to blame for a possible anomaly. However, as this is all based on speculation I will simply treat it as a mission success until anything else is confirmed from officials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018 promises to be pretty amazing with tons of cool stuff just around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here welcome to kNews for week 01/2018, happy new year and as always a big shout out to my kNews boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first things first, there is a launch this week on Saturday which is a SpaceX Falcon 9 and I already covered that one in episode 46/2017. If you can call that cover at all, because there is or was not much to talk about since it’s the super secret military payload called Zuma. The launch was delayed from early December due to some issues with its payload fairing and it will finally take off from Cape Canaveral this weekend. If they will run into no further delays which would also delay number 1 on my list of things I look most forward to this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is of course SpaceX and their biggest Falcon Heavy rocket. The launch is scheduled for January 2018 and basically features 3 Falcon 9 boosters strapped together pushing the upper stage to ludicrous speeds. Hold on to your helmets guy, this will be quick and loud. Ontop will be of course a cherry red Tesla Roadster and if you wonder why on earth would somebody do that make sure to subscribe because I will talk about that in one of the next episodes. Seeing the first images of Falcon Heavy on the pad recently was just unreal. I really hope everything will go well and that we will very soon see this beast fly on a regular basis. I mean why not, it certainly won’t lie around and do nothing while SpaceX has two pads available in Florida. And just btw., out mothership the earth with also have a close encounter with Mars in the following months so I would not be surprised if we’d see more thing flying to the red planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next one on my list is at the exact opposite of the spectrum when it comes to rocket size. The launch date has yet to be announced but what I am also excited about in 2018 is VirginOrbit’s LauncherOne. It’s about time that rockets start to launch off planes more often and while there is Orbital ATK’s Pegasus, it really isn’t that present in my videos. While LauncherOne will start off as an expendable rocket to prove the concept, later iterations maybe called LauncherTwo and Three will hopefully get their wings and heat shields. Virgin Orbit’s Cosmic Girl is said to be able to carry two LauncherOnes at once which should be enough capability to launch a slightly bigger reusable rocket. However, that’s still in the realm of speculation at this point and depends on the outcome of the first flights. Everyone’s eyes are probably on SpaceX and the more success they have especially on the business side, the more companies will develop their own reusable system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number three comes in three separate yet similar events. SpaceX, Lockheed Martin and Boeing are all developing new spacecraft which will be further tested and flown this year. It’s the Dragon 2 for SpaceX, Orion for Lockheed Martin and the CST-100 Starliner for Boeing. All three will launch this year while at least Dragon and Orion will have spectacular inflight abort tests. For that they will be shot on top a rocket up to maximum aerodynamic pressure where they will go through the most dangerous escape scenario. This was of course extensively simulated on computers before the spaceships were even built, but it’s still always extremely nerve wrecking to see those capsules in reality blasting off their carrier rocket below mid flight. In case of SpaceX Falcon 9 I hope we will see the booster land although I’m not quite sure if it can take such forces without a nose cone. Its normal separation is performed way above the atmosphere where there is very little pressure left to harm the booster. Orion will be launched on top a Peacekeeper missile so the chances to recover that one are low although who knows, maybe they’ll mount a parachute on it for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, speaking of Dragon 2 we will likely not only see the abort test but also its first crewed flight to the ISS this year. I assume it will first do another uncrewed mission like Dragon 1 before that but even then it will be cool to watch Dragon to dock autonomously to it for the first time. And of course, while very unlikely to happen in 2018 there is also the crewed Dragon 2 mission around the moon which is currently scheduled for the end of the year. Should that happen it would be the first time humans went back to the moon after the Apollo program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes we haven’t been nowhere near the moon for almost 50 years. Many renditions of the moon make it appear extremely close to earth but the distance is in fact insane. 380,000 kms, this is a thousand times more distant than astronauts orbiting earth on the ISS. Slingshotting around the moon makes it look much larger than earth which must be a really strange feeling. It will probably take weeks before those people can comprehend what they experienced. Watching outside the windows will feel more like a movie, completely surreal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that all depends on the outcome of the upcoming Falcon Heavy mission and while I personally don’t think human will go around the moon this year, Dragon 2 will very likely. Should its first ride to space be on a Falcon Heavy SpaceX said they will launch it around the moon on a similar trajectory the tourists are planned to be launched. The cool thing about that is I’m sure we would get the best live moon flyby footage there has ever been. Imagine there would be a livestream of Dragon Flying by the moon and you could maybe switch between different cameras. How awesome would that be? Now I can’t wait for it..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course there will be dozens if not hundreds of other launches in 2018 and everyone has its purpose. I’m also pretty sure there are some incredibly important ones I didn’t think about or just don’t know so please, make sure to let me know in the comments on what you look most forward to this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, That shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehn and Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="what-i-look-forward-to" /><category term="list" /><category term="01-2018" /><summary type="html">In kNews for Week 01/2018 I talk about the recent ZUMA launch of SpaceX and what I look forward to in 2018!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_012018.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX Falcon 9 and Japan’s H-IIA launch!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/SpaceX-Falcon9-Iridium-H-IIA-JAXA-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX Falcon 9 and Japan's H-IIA launch!" /><published>2017-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/SpaceX-Falcon9-Iridium-H-IIA-JAXA-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/SpaceX-Falcon9-Iridium-H-IIA-JAXA-launch.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 51/2017 I speak about the launches of SpaceX Falcon 9 and Japan’s H-IIA going more into detail on how SpaceX’ going to recover their fairings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/23): Both rockets launched successfully and SpaceX surprisingly controlled the booster’s descent for a rather soft touchdown. It is unknown but also unlikely that the booster survived this maneuver. Launching to sun synchronous polar orbits means to launch along the earth’s terminator which separates the light from the dark at dawn. The cool part about this is while the sky is dark from a certain perspective, the rocket’s exhaust plume shines brightly in the sky being lit from the sun. This led to a social media storm about UFO sightings and what not on the US west coats. Pretty funny but also dangerous because there were multiple reported car accidents partly caused by this magnificent event. The drivers are obviously at fault because they have to keep their eyes on the road but it’s nonetheless an issue which could be overcome by giving out a radio warning in the future. Especially people who are completely unaware of rocket launches freaked out about seeing the ever expanding exhaut plume in the evening sky.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX launches its Falcon 9, Japan HII-A and…. what is that. (dum dum dum)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey guys, Lukas here, welcome to kNews for week 51 and as always a big shout out to my kNews boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust! And of course, thanks to SquarePants for sponsoring this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, jokes aside. The first rocket this week is Japan’s H-IIA beating SpaceX Falcon 9 by one minute launching on December 23rd at 1:26 UTC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top HII-A are the Global Change Observation Mission and a Super Low Altitude Test Satellite or SLATS for short. Both will be shot into a sun synchronous polar orbit and latter will slowly decrease its altitude below 200 km where it will demonstrate how satellites can be operated on such super low altitudes. Orbiting closer to ground allows a satellite to not only create more detailed images but it also simply orbits faster to make more orbits per day. It’s actually quite interesting because it has a very flat profile like a rod and solar panels which look like fins. This unusual body will allow it to consume fewer fuel than an ordinary one by minimizing the drag and therefore fuel consumption to offset the thicker air density. Sounds ideal for massive communication satellite constellations like the one SpaceX is planning since out of control satellites would burn up pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second rocket to launch as mention a minute later is SpaceX Falcon 9. It will take off from Vandenberg at 1:27 UTC and will not attempt to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason is not the payload because the 10 Iridium satellites are well within Falcon 9’s margins to return the booster to the drone ship and SpaceX has done so 3 times in the past already. But more on that in just a minute. Up top are Iridium 31 to 40 from a total of 75. The upper stage and the booster are below. Since it will not attempt to land there is no need for grid fins or landing legs so it will fly without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to H-IIA before Falcon 9 will also head for a polar orbit and tilt south right after lift off. This gravity turn is necessary to not only get to space but stay there just in case you are new to my channel. A satellite flies in circles called orbits quickly to fight gravity pulling it towards the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way there the main booster will stage away once its empty which is normally when SpaceX performs their one of a kind maneuver to land it back on a ship. However, not so today so the complete rocket will just crash into the ocean and become some kind of reef deep down under the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this was not officially published yet but there are some rumours. One states that the drone ship is not operational and on its way to the east coast for the upcoming Falcon Heavy launch because the other ship is damaged. However, another rumour is completely different from that saying SpaceX just doesn’t need another old booster core. They have almost a dozen piling up already and you just can’t sell such hardware on ebay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular booster is an older and used one from type Block 3. SpaceX is already flying Block 4 and Block 5 is just around the corner. Only the latest version will include the necessary changes to make it really reusable to fly more than twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, if you’re more interested into the Iridium payload I actually have a Special episode on that one you can check out if you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in the end I want to talk about the SpaceX MEGAKRAKEN. I made that name up to be honest but SpaceX has really built a kraken like ship. It is named Mr.Steven and features 4 gigantic arms in the back which look like they wanted to give someone a big hug. Or like a funny doodle. However, this ship has a very special use case and that is of course to catch the rockets fairings or at least one of them. I don’t know if it will be used this time around but it is at the Los Angeles port waiting for action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How this would look like is a little speculative so please take this with a grain of salt. While the ship waits in the middle of the ocean like the drone ship, the fairings separate from the rocket and begin they glide down to re-enter back into the atmosphere. Keeping them from tumbling around out of control are cold gas thrusters similar to what the booster uses to orient itself. It’s basically just highly pressurized gas which is released in puffs through a small nozzle. Very inefficient but also very simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once within the atmosphere the fairing would start by releasing a small inflated ball which it drags behind it to stabilize the atmospheric flight. Once below a certain speed the same ball would be used to pull out the steerable parachute. It would then glide towards the ship which would slowly speed up. On the ship could be some kind of lights maybe the fairing would follow once up close. It would keep the same heading and slowly descent to land on a net, stretched out around the four gigantic arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if this is a test and the second fairing will just crash into the ocean or if the crew can get the fairing off the net quickly enough for the second to land as well. The first could take a quicker route downwards while the other one would fly in circles like a hungry Falcon around the ship. It sounds really complicated but once everything is stable it should fly like a normal glider. Way easier than landing a booster. Whatever will happen I really really hope we will finally see some footage of it. That would be a cool christmas present!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of it, I wish you a merry christmas guys and in case there will be no more video next week also a happy new year. Okay, that shall conclude this episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. Auf Wiedersehen and thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2017" /><category term="spacex" /><category term="falcon-9" /><category term="JAXA" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="H-IIA" /><category term="51-2017" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 51/2017 I speak about the launches of SpaceX Falcon 9 and Japan’s H-IIA going more into detail on how SpaceX’ going to recover their fairings.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_512017.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Blue Origin’s New Shepard launched secretly!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blue Origin’s New Shepard launched secretly! " /><published>2017-12-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/Blue-Origin-New-Shepard-Capsule-2.0.html">&lt;p&gt;Blue Origin’s New Shepard rocket shot their brand new “Crew Capsule 2.0” into a sub orbital trajectory above the Mojave desert. This happened on December 12th 2017 and was as far as I know not streamed live nor announced, so I call it secret! Blue Origin was founded by Jeff Bezos who is also the head at the e-commerce giant amazon. Next to New Shepard, Blue Origin is also working on its orbital class launch vehicle called New Glenn which will use 7 BE-4 engines burning liquid methane and oxygen on its first stage, unlike New Shepard which burns liquid Hydrogen. However, New Shepard’s BE-3 engine will probably be used on an expendable third stage of the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Shepard seems to have been upgraded being called the “next generation booster” and the capsule now finally features real windows - which were previously only painted on. Shooting the capsule straight up it almost passed the Karman line at 99 km at its highest point - the Apoapsis. This was therefore strictly speaking not a “space flight” but it doesn’t really make a difference to the payload whether you cross 100 km or not. The border of 100 km arises from aviation where a plane traveling at this altitude had to reach orbital velocity in order to gain enough lift from its wings to stay up. This is because of the extremely low, yet existing air pressure and means wings are not needed anymore once above orbital velocity and 100 km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both capsule and booster landed successfully afterwards and New Shepard once again delivered a pinpoint arrival on its landing area, which by the way got a new paint job. It could be similar to SpaceX’ one a more radar reflective material to enhance the accuracy, which could also double as a more durable coating to the extremely hot exhaust gas. However, that’s just speculation on my end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onboard Crew Capsule 2.0 was no crew but not further specified commercial, educational and research equipment. On suborbital parabolic flights like these cargo still experiences weightlessness for a few seconds to minutes, which is enough time to perform many different experiments that are just better suited for free fall. An example for this would be the ice crystal formation in clouds. Watching droplets freeze in mid air is very hard to achieve in the lab. You can of course watch entire steam clouds freezing but individual particles not so much. In such a free fall environment on the other hand you can make droplets hover just in front a microscope to observe how they form to gain a better understanding of what is actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the below linked video carefully you will also notice different reflective properties on the capsule windows. Some are highly reflective like chrome while others look much more see-through and dark. The purpose is unknown at the moment but could either be related to the experiments hiding behind them, or Blue Origin could be testing different window materials to figure out what is best for its future tourists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The radiation especially in the Ultraviolet range (UV) is extremely high above the atmosphere and potential tourist eyes have to be protected from that. Adding reflective coating is not hard but comes with the big downside of also reflecting visible light you want to enjoy during flight coming off of earth. It would definitely lower the overall experience if everything would look like you’d watch through extremely dark sunglasses. The future will tell what Blue Origin will come up with but I’m positive they will figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ZJghIk7_VA&quot; class=&quot;inverted&quot;&gt;Mannequin Skywalker’s Ride to Space&lt;/a&gt; by Blue Origin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="november" /><category term="2017" /><category term="Blue-Origin" /><category term="New-Shepard" /><category term="Jeff-Bezos" /><category term="Crew-Capsule-2.0" /><summary type="html">Blue Origin’s New Shepard rocket shot their brand new “Crew Capsule 2.0” into a sub orbital trajectory above the Mojave desert. This happened on December 12th 2017 and was as far as I know not streamed live nor announced, so I call it secret! Blue Origin was founded by Jeff Bezos who is also the head at the e-commerce giant amazon. Next to New Shepard, Blue Origin is also working on its orbital class launch vehicle called New Glenn which will use 7 BE-4 engines burning liquid methane and oxygen on its first stage, unlike New Shepard which burns liquid Hydrogen. However, New Shepard’s BE-3 engine will probably be used on an expendable third stage of the rocket.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22004_New-Shepard-Crew-Capsule.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Astronauts and 4 Rockets Launch!</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Astronauts and 4 Rockets Launch!" /><published>2017-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/videos/Rocket-Labs-Electron-Still-Testing.html">&lt;p&gt;In kNews for week 50/2017 I mainly talk about the upcoming Soyuz launch to the ISS carrying three astronauts, but I also mention three other launches namely: Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9 and Arianespace’s Ariane 5!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/17): To round off the week Soyuz brought its astronauts to space safely. The Soyuz spacecraft will dock to the station on Tuesday December 19th which is the long track to the ISS. I’m not entirely sure why they chose this longer profile but it might be due to SpaceX’s Dragon capsule which arrived on Sunday. However, it could also be the other way around so that Dragon was allowed to launch just because Soyuz would chose the longer profile. Either way, best luck to those astronauts sitting in their tin can far above the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/16): Rocket Lab decided to give their staff some rest and push their Electron launch into 2018 due to some issues with the rocket and the weather. Better safe than sorry I would say.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/15): SpaceX Falcon 9 had a successful launch delivering Dragon into a low earth orbit while landing its booster at Landing Zone 1. There is only one launch left this year for SpaceX which will take place in Vanderberg. Should this one succeed SpaceX will leave 2017 with a perfect flight record without a failure. That’s not as self-evident as it might seem because SpaceX are constantly changing their hardware releasing new version of their boosters frequently. This year we moved from Block 3 to Block 4 while the final Block 5 is just around the corner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2017/12/13): Ariane 5 brought its 4 passengers named Nicole, Zofia, Alexandre and Irina (drawing competition winners) into their desired circular medium earth orbits. They will now individually raise their trajectory over the course of several weeks until they can be put into service at their constellation slots. Adding 4 satellites will enhance the accuracy and availability of the GALILEO navigation system because more satellites means the chance to have some of them in the sky above is higher. It takes 4 to determine a location successfully but the more the better. Congratulations to Arianespace and ESA!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-script&quot;&gt;Video Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three astronauts go to space and four rockets launch, now on kNews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Lukas here welcome to kNews for week 50 and as always a big shout out to my kNews boosters on Patreon. Thanks for your thrust!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I come to the launches I want to announce some changes to kNews. I used to try push out one video per week covering all the launches in great detail, which to be honest, is just too much. I tried to be fair and treat all payloads and rockets the same but even I have to say communication satellite number 105 is just not as exciting to talk about even though every rocket launch is cool to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to pick out one topic per week which I will put my heart and soul into while only mentioning all the upcoming launches briefly in the beginning. Now, this is all not set in stone and I will listen to your feedback on that carefully to make some adjustments. The topic I focus on could be a particular launch but it could also be something else like a Special episode. My main goal is to release one episode per week consistently which I still fail to deliver very often. Anyways, let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching this week are Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9, Ariane 5 and a Soyuz. Three of them might actually launch on the same day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up is Electron which has a rather loose schedule. It could launch any day of the week at 1:30 UTC from the Rocket Lab Launch Complex 1 in New Zealand. The main constraint is the weather I believe. Up top are 4 Cubesats, two of each from type Flock-2 and Lemur-2. All these are equipped with cameras to take picture from the ground below and are part of large Cubesat constellation belonging to the companies Planet Labs and Spire Global.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is a SpaceX Falcon 9 with an inaugural flight from Space Launch Complex 40 on Tuesday at 16:46 UTC. The launch pad bas broken due to a Falcon 9 exploding last year but it’s back. This means the other pad 39 can be finally changed to support Falcon Heavy. Up top Falcon 9 is a Dragon 1 spacecraft filled with cargo for the International Space Station. To get there it will be shot into a low earth orbit inclined at 51.6 degrees. The same one the ISS is orbiting at but of course just a little lower to catch up with it. A special thing to mention here is the booster and the capsule are both flight proven as SpaceX is referring to their reused hardware. The turnaround time is still very high but Block 5, the final iteration of Falcon 9, is not yet flying. Block 5 will include a lot of changes which make reusing the booster easier to finally step up the re-launch game to ultimately increase the launch cadence immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number three on the list is an Ariane 5 hopefully causing a rumble in the jungle on Tuesday as well at 18:36 UTC in Kourou, French Guiana. Up top are two GALILEO navigation satellites which will be shot into a 56 degrees inclined transfer orbit. Their destination is one of three medium earth orbital planes with an altitude of roundabout 22,000 km. The navigation constellation is not yet finished and Arianespace will continue to build it up for the european union to be a little more independent from the US GPS and Russia’s GLONASS which are quite similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last launch this week aims for the International Space Station as well but that one is filled with astronauts so I will of course feature it in greater detail. It’s a Soyuz rocket currently scheduled to lift off on Sunday at 07:21 UTC from Baikonur in Kazakhstan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up top the Soyuz rocket is the Soyuz spacecraft hiding behind a tight fairing. The pointy tower up top is the escape system which is basically a solid fueled booster firing its engines to the sides should something go wrong. It would separate the crew from the rocket in the early stages of the flight. However, it will be staged away mid flight once the rocket is in space to get rid of the weight since the spacecraft could separate from the rocket on its own should its engines fail. The escape system is also only designed for an in-atmospheric abort using grid fins to steer it at high speeds. This wouldn’t work in space and an abort so late into the mission could cause the capsule to tumble and spin uncontrollably. This would be very dangerous and life threatening for the astronauts on board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned Soyuz will launch from Baikonur and head north east to follow an inclination of 51.6 degrees. As it speeds into the sky its flight computer will do most of the work and drop its empty stages on the way up. Since these empty tanks drop on ground Roscosmos actually has a ground crew to locate the crash sites and return the boosters. I’m not sure what they do with them but I guess there are some valuable materials on that rocket which could be recycled into new rockets. However, that’s just my speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rocket heads up in the background let me introduce to you the astronauts joining Expedition 54 on the ISS. For Russia we have Anton Shkaplerov. He is 45 years old and was born in Ukraine. His career started as a Russian Air Force pilot and he later on graduated in Air Force Engineering. So far Anton has spent a year in space and by a year I really mean 365 days to be precise. Ahem, he was twice aboard the station already once in 2012 and once in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is Kanai Norishige from Japan. He turns 41 this month and is a military doctor who did specialise in surgery I think. He later transferred to the Japan Self Defense Force Hospital in Kure which lies in the Hiroshima district of Japan. There he become a Diving Medical Officer after he has qualified himself as a diver in the US Navy. This will be his first flight to space where his diving experience could really pay off but I’m not sure if he will participate in any extravehicular activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally on board is also an US astronaut namely Scott Manley, err, I mean Scott Tingle. He is 52 years old and was born in Attleboro, Massachusetts. This gotta be one of the hardest to pronounce english words. Holy moly. Massachusetts. Anyways, Scott’s career is also dominated by military service as most astronauts. He is a commander in the US Navy and a test pilot. This will be also he first mission to space after he has qualified as an astronaut in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish these brave astronauts all the best luck on their ride to the station and of course also a nice christmas and new years eve they will share with the other crew members awaiting their arrival on the ISS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, that shall conclude this week’s episode and I hope to see you in the next one if you like. This show is mainly supported by crowdfunding so please consider to become a kNews Booster if you can spare a dollar or two. I’m currently saving for better hardware to render all those animations you see more quickly. Again big thanks to all who have supported me so far. Auf Wiedersehn and Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="videos" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rocket" /><category term="launch" /><category term="2017" /><category term="spacex" /><category term="falcon-9" /><category term="soyuz" /><category term="ariane-5" /><category term="rocket-lab" /><category term="Electron" /><category term="50-2017" /><summary type="html">In kNews for week 50/2017 I mainly talk about the upcoming Soyuz launch to the ISS carrying three astronauts, but I also mention three other launches namely: Rocket Lab’s Electron, SpaceX’ Falcon 9 and Arianespace’s Ariane 5!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22thumb_502017.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">SpaceX to Launch Tesla Roadster to Mars</title><link href="http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SpaceX to Launch Tesla Roadster to Mars" /><published>2017-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.knews.space/news/SpaceX-to-launch-Tesla-to-Space.html">&lt;p&gt;Yep, it’s not a joke (as it seems). SpaceX’ Falcon Heavy will launch Elon Musk’s red Tesla Roaster to Mars on its maiden flight in January 2018 according to a tweet by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/936782477502246912&quot;&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt;. My illustration up top shows a Tesla Model X because this is the only one I got modeled in 3D which I used in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fYuvOMnDRdc&quot;&gt;Tesla Project Loveday&lt;/a&gt;” entry. However, it is still unclear whether it will be one of the new 200 kWh Roadsters which will arrive at the market by 2020, or one if not the first Tesla Roadster Elon Musk ever owned himself. This would be quite emotional and a real loss for him should something go wrong! &lt;em&gt;knocks on wood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.knews.space/assets/img/003_Musk-Tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elon Musk Tweet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Falcon Heavy is SpaceX’ yet heaviest and most powerful rocket to fly. Due to unexpected difficulties when it comes to “simply strapping more Falcon boosters to Falcon 9”, the maiden flight was delayed back multiple times. It was first accounced to fly in 2012 which was of course a very optimistic timeframe to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in space and separated from the rocket, the Tesla Roadster will coast to Mars and do a close flyby performing a swing-by or gravity assist around the red planet. Due to the lack of propulsion the Roadster will not be able to enter into a stable orbit and will instead be shot into outter space maybe even visiting other planets. However, this is just my speculation because no further details have been published yet. It’s unlikely that SpaceX would build a full-fledged spacecraft around the Roadster though. I assume attachments will mostly consist of solar panels, cameras and communication equiptment to send its data back to earth. A gyroscope or some cold gas thrusters would also make sense to change its orientation and maybe some basic radiators to keep its batteries cool. But who knows, maybe I’m completely wrong and they will turn the Roadster into Lone Starr’s Eagle 5. &amp;amp;128526;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its journey it will of course take a lot of images like selfies from itself and Mars and maybe Phobos or Deimos too - Mars’ moons. What seems rediculous is actually just part of a very risky test flight. Elon Musk himself said, he would consider it a “win” if the rocket clears the towers and does not cause any damage to the launch site. Other rockets often also use so called dummy payloads on test flights but these are of course usually much less exciting or at least not further detailed. There could be a lot cool and silly stuff in space we don’t know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Falcon Heavy ignites 27 Merlin engines during launch which all shoot out their exhaust gases at speeds above the speed of sound. This leads to shock waves forming similar to sonic booms which not only hit the ground, but also reflect back at the vehicle making it hard to predict if everything will go well. SpaceX uses water cannons to fill the air with tiny droplets absorbing hopefully enough of the shock wave’s energy to keep dangerous oscillations away from Falcon Heavy’s highly pressurized body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.knews.space/assets/img/003_falcon-heavy-exhaust.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Falcon Heavy Exhaust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally think this is a brilliant marketing move - even if it’s not intented to be one - and might open up space to much more then just “rational” payloads. A Falcon Heavy is able to shoot 17 metric tons of payload to Mars in its expendable setup, maybe half of that as a reuseable rocket which would be still enough to shoot hundreds of mummified human remains to the red planet. Humanity would finally fulfill its dream to rest in peace among the stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lukas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dec. 3rd: There is some new information about the story not being true and made up by Elon Musk, but these don’t refer to official tweets just a talk between Musk and TheVerge. Knowing Musk’s sense of humor a little I personally think he would rather troll TheVerge than to admit lying. At this point if it was indeed a joke it would be a toy Tesla glued to the payload playing music. That would still be a Tesla flying to Mars. Future will tell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dec. 2nd: I just noticed Elon Musk answered a question about the model of the car in the comments below his tweet. It will be a first generation Tesla Roadster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Lukas</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="knews" /><category term="space" /><category term="rockets" /><category term="november" /><category term="2017" /><category term="SpaceX" /><category term="Falcon-Heavy" /><category term="Mars" /><category term="Tesla" /><category term="Elon-Musk" /><summary type="html">Yep, it’s not a joke (as it seems). SpaceX’ Falcon Heavy will launch Elon Musk’s red Tesla Roaster to Mars on its maiden flight in January 2018 according to a tweet by Elon Musk. My illustration up top shows a Tesla Model X because this is the only one I got modeled in 3D which I used in my Tesla Project Loveday” entry. However, it is still unclear whether it will be one of the new 200 kWh Roadsters which will arrive at the market by 2020, or one if not the first Tesla Roadster Elon Musk ever owned himself. This would be quite emotional and a real loss for him should something go wrong! knocks on wood</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://www.knews.space/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22003_SpaceX-Falcon9-Tesla.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3E%22%22%7D" /></entry></feed>