<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>kNews Space</title>
		<description>Rocket Launch and Space News</description>
		<link></link>
		<atom:link href="/rss-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>DeepJeb Lives!</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Sort of… but let’s begin from all the way back, a whole week ago. I challenged myself to learn how to code an “A.I.” this year. That’s - next to 1440p - one of my new year’s resolutions! (haha)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/deepjeb-lives.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/deepjeb-lives.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Rocket Launch Briefing 11/2018</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;First up in November was a Chinese Long March 3B. The rocket has 3 core stages, 4 strap-on boosters and an optional 4th stage which is only used to kick navigation satellites into their medium earth orbits. This was not the case on this particular mission despite the satellite being from type BeiDou, which is meant to enhance the chinese GPS. However, BeiDou uses a mix of medium earth orbits and geosynchronous slots above China. It’s hard to find real images of these so simply picture a wrapped box with foldable solar panels attached. These are not designed to be pretty as nobody can see them up there, but that will actually change in the future as satellites will get bigger and heavier. Satellite makers like SSL from California, are already developing satellites that can assemble themselves on orbit, using a robotic arm. Their particular system is called Dragonfly and I bet we’ll get some nice satellite selfies in the future, as these are of course equipped with cameras. In case you wonder: the more unfoldable parts there are, the more hinges and springs and motors you need to unfold it. At some point it therefore makes sense to simply mount an arm like at the Space Station! Stacking stuff is also a little easier on the mounting points as they don’t have to secure the hardware while going through the forces and vibrations of a rocket launch.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/briefings/rocket-launches-november-2018.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/briefings/rocket-launches-november-2018.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A &quot; Brief &quot; Introduction</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Rocket Launch Briefings will initially give you a quick or &lt;em&gt;brief&lt;/em&gt; overview about a month’s rocket launches. I have not yet decided whether I will cover them monthly or weekly but monthly is definitely a more eye catchy format I think. “Rocket Launch Briefing - November 2018” sounds more like something people would watch in retrospect. Meaning, it’s not that much effort to watch 12 episodes in order to get an overview about a full year, rather than 52 episodes! I will of course pick out topics I find most interesting and make separate videos about them in the other new video format I currently call my “Video Logbook” aka. a Vlog. I will talk rather casually about something while playing back an animation that I got inspired to. Nothing too fancy and also rather compact!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/briefings/a-brief-introduction.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/briefings/a-brief-introduction.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>What is SpaceX Starlink?</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;The dotted white outer rim to the sides shows regular communication satellites in a geosynchronous orbit. There are roughly 500 or these currently in orbit and most of you will know them from satellite television. Yep, that’s where you point your dishes at. The ISS orbits much more closely at 400 km, in fact it’s so close you wouldn’t even notice its in space at all from up here. The red dot zips across the sky at 8 km/s in order to not fall back to ground. It counters gravity with its own inertia like a giant centrifuge.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-starlink-explained.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-starlink-explained.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>How Dangerous are Black Holes?</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Black Holes are among the most mysterious objects in the sky but, how dangerous are they? I want to explore this question in this logbook entry and give you are quick summary of how I understand the topic. Please be aware that I’m not an astrophysicist and can only share my view which may have som flaws! My main inspiration is the thought of such a hole flying by our sun! I never really thought about how dangerous this seemingly innocent event could be?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/how-dangerous-black-holes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/how-dangerous-black-holes.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>SpaceX Second Stage Reuse!</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;This logbook entry is about Falcon’s not yet but hopefully soon reusable upper stage. As every space enthusiast is aware of, SpaceX is recovering and reusing their first stage boosters. The first stage turns around and guides itself like a missile after separation, using grid fins to hit its target drone ship out in the ocean. Then, just before impact, up to three engines ignite to land on the floating platform which is stabilized and held in place by the ship’s extremely powerful and foldable propellers. This still one of a kind maneuver is what makes SpaceX so different from other rocket companies which all throw away their boosters crashing them into the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-falcon-second-stage-reuse.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-falcon-second-stage-reuse.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>SpaceX BFR Issues Explained!</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk recently unveiled SpaceX new BFR design to bring humans to Mars and how to fund  it. In this logbook entry I want to share my thoughts on 3 commonly pointed out issues which raise a lot of questions. You are of course free to share your view and I’m looking forward to some debates!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-bfr-issues-explained.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.knews.space/vlogs/spacex-bfr-issues-explained.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
